<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Clement, the blessed Paul's fellow-labourer in the Gospel, his first epistle to the Corinthians: being an effectuall suasory to peace, and brotherly condescension, after an unhappy schism and separation in that Church. From whence the understanding reader may receive satisfaction concerning the businesse of episcopacy, or presbytery, as it stood in the age of the Apostles, and some time after. The ancient'st writing the Church hath, and the onely extant to that purpose, next to the divinely-inspired Scriptures. And being made good use of, may prove a remedy against the breaches and sad divisions of these distracted churches and times.</title>
            <title>First epistle of Clement to the Corinthians</title>
            <author>Clement I, Pope.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E396_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E396_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862161</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862161</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160356</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E396[24] or 63:E396[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Clement, the blessed Paul's fellow-labourer in the Gospel, his first epistle to the Corinthians: being an effectuall suasory to peace, and brotherly condescension, after an unhappy schism and separation in that Church. From whence the understanding reader may receive satisfaction concerning the businesse of episcopacy, or presbytery, as it stood in the age of the Apostles, and some time after. The ancient'st writing the Church hath, and the onely extant to that purpose, next to the divinely-inspired Scriptures. And being made good use of, may prove a remedy against the breaches and sad divisions of these distracted churches and times.</title>
                  <title>First epistle of Clement to the Corinthians</title>
                  <author>Clement I, Pope.</author>
                  <author>Burton, William, 1609-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.Y. for J.P. and O.P. and are to be sold in Paul's Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLVII. [1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated and annotated by William Burton, who has signed the dedication.</note>
                  <note>In two parts. Part 2 has a separate dated t.p.: Certaine annotations upon Clement; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Second epistle of Clement to the Corinthians is not by Clement, but by an anonymous author.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 5th".</note>
                  <note>Part 2 = Thomason E.396[25].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church history --  Primitive and early church, ca. 30-600 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160356:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE ANNOTATIONS UPON CLEMENT: Intended as well for the <hi>aſſerting</hi> of this Epiſtle, againſt ſome Exceptions, in reſpect of the <hi>Author</hi> of it, and his <hi>manner of writing;</hi> as for the preventing of others:</p>
            <p>But eſpecially for vindicating it from <hi>Miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>allegations,</hi> and <hi>wrong citations,</hi> urged out of it, in regard of ſome points concerning <hi>Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch-government,</hi> in controverſie at this day.</p>
            <p>Containing alſo ſome other Obſervations, whereby the Authour is illuſtrated.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>C. Lucilius</hi> apud Cic lib. 2. de Orat.</bibl> PERSIUM <hi>non curo legere:</hi> Laelium Decimum <hi>volo.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Y.</hi> for <hi>J. P.</hi> and <hi>O. P.</hi> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, in the Yeare of our Lord, M.DC.XLVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:160356:2"/>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:160356:2"/>
            <head>A SUMMARY of chief Matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe Annotations, obſerved out of this EPISTLE.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> THe Equality as well of <hi>Churches</hi> themſelves, as of their <hi>Governours,</hi> in the firſt Age. <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> what kind of Biſhops. The cauſe of the diſagreement among Writers concerning the Order and Succeſsion of the firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome. Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> common names at that time. The humility of them in thoſe times.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> At what time, as is moſt probable, this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> might be written. <hi>Baronius</hi> commended for collecting the <hi>Fragments</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Of the <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and <hi>Factions</hi> among the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his firſt Epiſtle to them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> A place in <hi>Clement</hi> cited by <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Clement</hi> to be underſtood of the <hi>Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,</hi> though meant of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Governours,</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> notwithſtanding the likeneſſe of ſtile, which is ſaid to be in both theſe Epiſtles.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> The Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> the Martyr hath ſeverall paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages out of <hi>Clement.</hi> Whether it may not be thought genuine.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> The manner of citing places out of the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>New:</hi> Which alſo is to be obſerved in <hi>Clement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> The <hi>
                  <abbr>LXX.</abbr> Interpreters</hi> generally followed by the Apoſtles. Then leſſe corrupt then in after ages. Now not ſo much to be reſpected. The old <hi>Latine</hi> verſion of the <abbr>
                  <hi>LXX.</hi>
               </abbr> in ancient uſe here in <hi>Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9. Clement</hi> excuſed, in his instance of <hi>Aaron's</hi> and <hi>Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am's</hi> being ſhut out of the <hi>Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10. Clement,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Peter's</hi> Martyrdome, ſayes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:160356:3"/> of his being at <hi>Rome,</hi> much leſſe of his <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> there, and Prerogative. Whether he were ever there, or no, is diſcuſsed. His was the Apostleſhip of the <hi>Circumciſion.</hi> A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable breach in Church-Hiſtory from the <hi>Acts</hi> to <hi>Trajan's</hi> time. Whether <hi>Paul,</hi> as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> might not from <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment's</hi> words be thought to ſuffer under ſome <hi>Provinciall Magiſtrate,</hi> rather then at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11.</hi> Whether <hi>Paul</hi> ever performed his journie into <hi>Spain:</hi> Or were ever in <hi>Britain. Peter's</hi> being there, and ordaining <hi>Biſhops,</hi> confirmed by our Engliſh <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> either from very ſlight, or forged Authorities.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12. Clement's</hi> manner of urging Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13.</hi> A place in him out of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The ſeverall acceptions of it.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15.</hi> The <hi>Pillar</hi> of Salt, into which <hi>Lot's</hi> wife was turned, remaining in <hi>Clement's</hi> time.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16. Clement's</hi> citing a place in <hi>Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17.</hi> A ſentence of <hi>Clement's</hi> reſtored out of <hi>Jerome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18.</hi> A place in <hi>Matthew</hi> not ſo well rendred by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlators.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19. Moſes</hi> cited for <hi>David. Clement</hi> excuſed therein by many places in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> Joſephus, <hi>Scriptor Chriſtianus, Graecè,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Chriſt's</hi> diviſion of the <hi>Books</hi> of the Old Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Young's</hi> conjecture confirmed. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>The unpaſſable Ocean,</hi> meant by <hi>Clement</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>The Worlds beyond it,</hi> thought to be the Iſlands called the <hi>Britannies.</hi> A diſcourſe endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make it good.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22.</hi> The <hi>Phenix,</hi> an Emblem of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> among the ancient Chriſtians. The <hi>Reſurrection</hi> taken for a new <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> by the Philoſophers at <hi>Athens.</hi> How far a belief of the truth thereof poſſeſs'd the better ſort of <hi>Heathens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:160356:3"/>
               <hi>23.</hi> Of what is poſſible, or <hi>impoſſible</hi> with God. His <hi>Power</hi> alwaies accompanies his <hi>Will.</hi> We ought to ſpeak reverently of his <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24. Clement</hi> is defended about a place, which he is ſaid to cite out of the <hi>Wiſdom of Solomon.</hi> Of the <hi>Author</hi> of that Book, and the credit thereof. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe urgeth <hi>Heathen</hi> Writers: <hi>Menander</hi> the Comedian, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25. Clement</hi> abſolutely condemnes the Doctrine of <hi>Merits,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification</hi> by Works.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26.</hi> The happineſs of a Chriſtian Church in <hi>Clement's</hi> judgement.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27. Clement</hi> is falſly urged to prove <hi>ſet-times</hi> for publick Prayers in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, which they call <hi>Canonicall Houres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">
               <hi>28. Clement</hi> is not truly and faithfully alledged, to prove, that in the firſt Age there was a diſtinction between the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> and <hi>Laity.</hi> Neither doth it appeare by any genuine authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who is defended from contradicting of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> whereof he ſtands accuſed. <hi>Laicus</hi> and <hi>Catholicus,</hi> of what uſe in the firſt Age. Chriſtian <hi>Presbytery</hi> from the <hi>Jewiſh;</hi> and what that was.</p>
            <p n="29">
               <hi>29.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what they were. Henr. Stephani <hi>Gloſſarium Latino-Graecum</hi> emendatur. Victimarum <hi>probatio.</hi> Aruſpex.</p>
            <p n="30">
               <hi>30. Biſhop</hi> &amp; <hi>Presbyter;</hi> whence the Apoſtles borrowed theſe names. No <hi>diſtinction</hi> in matter of office, to be found of them in <hi>Clement.</hi> Nor any <hi>ſingle Biſhop</hi> of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in his time: Both which notwithſtanding are pretended out of him.</p>
            <p n="31">
               <hi>31.</hi> The <hi>Name</hi> of Epiſcopacy in <hi>Clement.</hi> Vocabulum <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris, quod Eccleſiae uſus obtinuit,</hi> in Auſtin. <hi>Biſhops</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt before theſe times. <hi>Chryſoſtome's</hi> riding on an <hi>Aſſe</hi> envied at. Not lawfull in his opinion for Biſhops to ride on <hi>horſe-back.</hi> The ſmall maintenance and poverty of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Britiſh, Iriſh,</hi> and other Country-Biſhops. The ambition, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:160356:4"/> and cruelty of the <hi>Roman</hi> taken notice of by an <hi>Heathen Hiſtorian.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, how taken in ancient Authors.</p>
            <p n="32">
               <hi>32.</hi> The Apoſtles power in <hi>conſtituting Biſhops</hi> &amp; <hi>Deacons</hi> conveyed unto <hi>others.</hi> Yet ſuch choice of Miniſters, according to <hi>Clement,</hi> is ineffectuall without the generall <hi>conſent of the people.</hi> A difficult thing to know <hi>who,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> kind of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> were firſt inſtituted by the Apoſtles. <hi>Euſebius</hi> his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to that purpoſe. Moſt <hi>Records</hi> of the firſt times utterly loſt.</p>
            <p n="33">
               <hi>33.</hi> A ſentence of <hi>Clement's</hi> ſeverally interpreted by <hi>ſix</hi> very learned men. Some of their <hi>various readings</hi> of it upon conjecture.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <hi>34. Clement</hi> not faithfully dealt withall. A <hi>tranſitive</hi> note added on purpoſe in the tranſlation of a paſſage of his into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> the better to make it appeare, that <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> are diſtinguiſht by him: Which notwithstanding appeares not out of him.</p>
            <p n="35">
               <hi>35. PAUL's Goſpel.</hi> What in <hi>Clement</hi> is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thereby. S. <hi>Johns</hi> firſt Epiſtle cited alſo under the Title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. No alteration of Church-government caus'd upon the <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as is urged. <hi>Jerome</hi> is therein defended.</p>
            <p n="36">
               <hi>36.</hi> Whether there were another <hi>Cephas</hi> beſides <hi>Peter.</hi> The place of <hi>Paul, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.12.</hi> underſtood of <hi>Peter</hi> by <hi>Clement,</hi> against ſome <hi>Interpreters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">
               <hi>37.</hi> A place of <hi>Clement's</hi> urged by <hi>Clement</hi> of Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria.</p>
            <p n="38">
               <hi>38.</hi> Another place of his alſo to be found in his writings.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <hi>39.</hi> A place of <hi>Clement's</hi> tranſlated by <hi>Jerom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="40">
               <hi>40. Epiphanius</hi> miſ-applies a paſſage in <hi>Clement. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom's</hi> imitation of the ſame place; and his golden <hi>Reſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">
               <hi>41. Clement</hi> excuſed, for urging the ſtory of <hi>Judith,</hi> by the example of the <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> who in their Epistles cite ſeverall <hi>Apocrypha</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> beſide <hi>Heathens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="42">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:160356:4"/>
               <hi>42.</hi> A place of ſome antient Gr. Tragedian perhaps alluded to by <hi>Clement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>43.</hi> The practice of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> government <hi>only</hi> aſſerted by this Epiſtle. The <hi>weightineſſe</hi> of the <hi>charge:</hi> and what care the <hi>people</hi> ought to have in the <hi>choice</hi> of ſuch as are to ſustain the burthen thereof.</p>
            <p n="44">
               <hi>44.</hi> A ſentence of <hi>Clement's,</hi> perhaps reſtored to this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle where the <hi>lacuna</hi> is, out of <hi>Baſil</hi> the <hi>Great. Clement's</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> cited by the Author of the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ad Orthodoxos.</hi> It is not <hi>Juſtin Martyrs.</hi> The antiquity and authority of the <hi>Sibyllin</hi> Verſes.</p>
            <p n="45">
               <hi>45.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This word borrowed by <hi>Polycarpus</hi> out of <hi>Clement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="46">
               <hi>46. Clement,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is defended againſt the cenſure of <hi>Photius,</hi> the Patriarch of <abbr>CP.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p n="47">
               <hi>47.</hi> Their names who carried this Epiſtle from <hi>Rome</hi> to the Church of <hi>Corinth. Fortunatus. Biton.</hi> The holy <hi>forgery</hi> of the Primitive times. <hi>Apocryphall Goſpels</hi> and <hi>Epiſtles</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Apoſtles, and other holy Mens names.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>ANNOTATIONS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church of God which ſo journeth at</hi> Rome, <hi>to the</hi> &amp;c.]<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>I.</abbr>
               </note> Two things may be obſerved from the very <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> of this <hi>Epistle.</hi> Firſt, The equality that was as well between theſe two Churches themſelves, as the Governors thereof, called <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church, and <hi>Biſhops;</hi> there being at this time no Superiority or prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, which notwithſtanding the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have ſince then affected. Secondly, That the <hi>Elders</hi> of both by themſelves, without any extraordinary <hi>Biſhop</hi> placed over them, did govern as well the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that of <hi>Corinth;</hi> it being very unlikely, that the names of them ſhould have been concealed in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:160356:5"/> this <hi>Inſcription,</hi> had either of the Churches had any one at that time in ſuch eminency of place, or power, above the other Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. For <hi>Clement</hi> was not now any ſingular, or<note n="*" place="margin">As he was not formerly at <hi>Philippi</hi> See <hi>H. Grotius</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scripture. Phil. 4.3. 2 Tim. 4.21.</note> onely Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor placed above the <hi>Preſb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tery</hi> thereof. But one of thoſe Miniſters, whoſe help the Apoſtles uſed in founding of Churches, <hi>Paul</hi> calling him his <hi>fellow-laborer;</hi> as was <hi>Linus</hi> alſo without queſtion, whom he mentions too; and both whom the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory makes Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome placing them both before <hi>Anacletus,</hi> and of the two, <hi>Linus</hi> firſt; ſome making <hi>Clement</hi> laſt of the three; but others again put him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either of the other two.<note place="margin">Cl. Salmaſ. diſſert. de Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcop. &amp; Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt. cap. 4.</note> Which confuſion the learned <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius</hi> conceives to proceed from no other cauſe, then that they were not particular and onely Biſhops, as the moſt would have them to be, but ſome of thoſe many Presbyters, who were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to govern the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with equall and joynt power. And truly the Reverend B<hi rend="sup">P</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Diſſert. de <hi>Ignatii,</hi> &amp;c. ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptis, cap. 18. in addend. p. 137. <hi>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um iſta ſcripſit</hi> Clemens, Epiſ. <hi>&amp;</hi> Preſ. <hi>communia ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c videantur fuiſſe nomina.</hi> Nicol. Vedel. Exercit. 8. in epiſt Ignat ad Maria. 11. ca. 3.</note> acknowledgeth, that when this Epiſtle was written by <hi>Clement</hi> the names of <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Preſbyter</hi> ſeemed to be common; as indeed thereby it appeares: though <hi>Vedelius,</hi> the Profeſſor of <hi>Geneva</hi> grant that this diſtinction was already<note n="*" place="margin">jam invaluiſſe.</note> grown for ſome good while to be in uſe in <hi>Clement</hi>'s time: which how it can be, <hi>Clement</hi>'s baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nay, Martyrdome, happening very preſently upon the writing thereof, as is moſt probably<note n="†" place="margin">v. Dn. Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Notas</hi> ad Clementem.</note> conjectured, I leave to others to conſider of. However it is a very good obſervation which the learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> maketh, that <hi>Clement</hi> being to exhort the diſagreeing and factious part of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to compliance and brotherly condeſcenſion in love and humility, he makes no uſe of any power from his own, but gently entreats them through the whole Epiſtle in the generall Name of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> never mentioning himſelf, or his own autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity any way: So unfitting a thing did thoſe holy men of the Primitive times conceive it to be, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] that I may uſe <hi>Clement</hi>'s own words, imperiouſly and arrogantly to advance themſelves over the flock and people of Chriſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſuch no part or portion at all in him: contrary to what we have ſeen, and have been very ſenſible of in our dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>II.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>The calamities and ſad accidents which have happened unto us.]</hi> All antiquity being wholly ſilent about the time when this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:160356:5"/> Epiſtle was written, learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> from theſe words, as alſo from a main circumſtance in <hi>Clement</hi>'s relation of <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, doth make a probable conjecture that it was ſent by him in the time of his baniſhment to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which was about the beginning of <hi>Trajan,</hi> or not long after, ſome two yeares before his martyrdome.<note place="margin">Baron. ad An. <abbr>XCV.</abbr> § 1.</note> The great <hi>Annalist</hi> refers the writing of it to the twelfth yeare of <hi>Domitian,</hi> ſome ſix, or ſeven years ſooner: But his <hi>Eminency</hi> pleaſes not to vouchſafe any ground or reaſon for his ſo doing. Yet his <hi>induſtry</hi> is very high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be honored, for that deſpairing ever to find an entire Copy, he firſt attempted to collect out of the Fathers writings, and ſet together, the unvaluable reliques of this<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb. l. 3. c. 12. Eccl. Hiſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Niceph. Call. lib. 3. cap. 18.</note> 
               <hi>admirable</hi> and<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iren. li. 3. c. 3. apud Euſeb.</note> 
               <hi>abſolute,</hi> (for ſo it was eſteemed of old,) and withall,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Valdè utilis.</hi> Hieron. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talog. Script. Eccleſiaſt.</note> 
               <hi>most uſefull</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; as it were the fragments and ſhattered parcells of ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable, but almoſt decayed ſtatue; being not the leſſe to be reſpected, for that it had undergon the ſame fate, which, by the meanes of bad times and worſe hands, many an excellent and choice piece hath met with, to the unſpeakable loſs and damage of poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abominable and ungodly ſedition.]<note place="margin">
                     <abbr>III.</abbr>
                  </note> Baronius</hi> makes the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> wherein he taxes them for their<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſchiſms</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>factions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad annum <abbr>LVII.</abbr> § 2.</note> to be written neer forty years before this of <hi>Clement.</hi> It ſhould ſeem very ſtrange, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the earneſt endevours of the Apoſtles, and their miniſters in the Goſpel, for ſettling of peace and unitie in this Church, their diviſions ſhould revive and again get head, with more ſtrength and obſtinacy, and grow more inveterate, as appeares by this preſent <hi>abominable</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> ſedition and breach among them;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem.</note> ſo ſoon did <hi>the enemy</hi> that <hi>evil one,</hi> begin to ſow his <hi>tares</hi> even in the pureſt times and Congregations, and ſo unhappily they thrived.<note place="margin">Eccl. hiſt. li. 3. cap. 12.</note> To work them to an agreement was this Epiſtle pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely written, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us out of <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> a very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient writer, (not the ſuppoſititious that is extant,) and <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For who hath ever ſojourned among you, that</hi> &amp;c.]<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>IV.</abbr>
               </note> This whole paſſage, and others following, are cited from hence by the other <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who lived after this <hi>Clement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I mean flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, ſomewhat above <abbr>CXX.</abbr> years.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:160356:6"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>V.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Them that are</hi> Governours <hi>over you.</hi>] The word in Greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Eccl. hiſt. l <abbr>III.</abbr> cap. 32. Catal. Scrip. Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and out of him <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerves that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the character of the phraſe in this Epiſtle is like that in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Ebrews,</hi> but that many even entire ſences, and very ſame words are heer borrowed from thence. So that <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> dare hereupon almoſt undertake, that <hi>Clement</hi> was the Tranſlator of that Epiſtle out of the <hi>Ebrew</hi> (in which language it is vulgarly thought <hi>Paul</hi> wrote it to his countrymen,) into <hi>Greek,</hi> as we now have it, rather then <hi>Luke.</hi> Yet however, this word hath a differing ſence heer from the uſe and ſignification of it in the laſt to the <hi>Ebrews,</hi> where it is taken for the <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church, as moſt plainly appeares by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection,<note place="margin">Ebr. 13.7.17.</note> and comparing of the 7. and 17. verſes. For in this place, and through the whole Epiſtle, where it is to be found, I am ſure ſeven times at leaſt, we muſt underſtand it of the <hi>Civill Magistrates,</hi> and their power, called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s language, <hi>to whom</hi> he bids <hi>every ſoul to be ſubject:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1. Tit. 3.1. <hi>Imperatoribus.</hi> Jun. <hi>Praefectis.</hi> Salmaſ.</note> and of whoſe ſuffering, and death, <hi>Clement</hi> making mention, he doth tell us in this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe, that it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, under the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> or their <hi>Governours.</hi> Neither ſignifies it otherwiſe in the other places. And ſo in like manner neither is the <hi>Preſbyterie</hi> of the Church intended by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the words next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, but the elderly ſort onely, as oppoſed to the youth: which whole ſentence of <hi>Clement</hi> is well illuſtrated by what we read in the <hi>Proëm</hi> to the Laws of <hi>Charondas</hi> of <hi>Catana:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r Fragm. Pythagoreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. himſelf elſwhere alſo joyning together <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> The Rulers, or Magiſtrates; the aged ſort; and the young men: And yet the <hi>Order</hi> it ſelf is abundantly aſſerted by him, as in oppoſition to ſolitary Epiſcopacy, in this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> as you will hear in what follows.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>VI.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nblameable and pure conſcience, loving their own huſbands.]</hi> Theſe very expreſſions, as alſo many others beſides, as may be ſeen in what followes, are borrowed out of <hi>Clement</hi> by <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus,</hi> that antient and faithfull witneſs of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the Scholler of <hi>John</hi> his <hi>beloved Diſciple,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians.</hi> This note is added, to this end and purpoſe, not onely to prove this Epiſtle to be genuine, and of that antiquity which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:160356:6"/> we believe it to be of, (which notwithſtanding is ſufficiently already made to appeare;) but alſo that a certain authority, and reſpect, given to it in time of moſt remote antiquity, (for in after ages it was publiquely read in<note n="a" place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 3. cap. 12. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. contra Ebionitas. Hieronym. in Catal.</note> Congregations, and Churches,) may be obſerved, and taken notice of. For to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> for ſpurious, and a ſuppoſititious birth, none, that I know of, have undertaken to do it. What paſſages<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. lib. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Photius Patr. <abbr>CP.</abbr> in Biblioth. num. 126.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and that diligent Greek Patriarch in his <hi>Bibliotheque</hi> long-ago cited out of it, are yet to be found in it. And the Church Hiſtorians of <hi>Madenburg,</hi> refer us to the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>antiquitatis ſcrutatores,</hi> themſelves having little, or nothing to any purpoſe, to ſay againſt it: eſpecially if we do conſider the ſimplicity and plainneſs<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.1.4. Andr. Rivetus Crit. Sacri li. 2. ca. 3. edit. ultima.</note> of the Apoſtolicall times, and ſtyle. They had better hearts; we indeed better tongues, and pens. But neither doth the judicious D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Rivet,</hi> that ſingular orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſometime of <hi>Leyden,</hi> take upon him to cenſure it. As for that Greek copy of it, onely mentioned by him,<note n="†" place="margin">Edit. <hi>Ignatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,</hi> p. 243. &amp; Not ad <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp.</hi> num. 1.</note> what the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> obſerved concerning it, and the credit it might have, all that periſhed in the late great ſchath-fire at <hi>Oxford,</hi> accompanied with other rare parcells of Church anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, to the no ſmall grief of all them, that make ſearch and enquiry after matters of this nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beloved hath eaten, and drunken,</hi> &amp;c.]<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>VII.</abbr>
               </note> This ſhort paſſage is the ſumme of three whole verſes out of the <abbr>XXXII.</abbr> Chapter of <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> It is the manner of <hi>Clement,</hi> and indeed of the Fathers after him generally, to cite places of Holy Scripture, not alwayes in their own words and ſentences, as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived there; thinking the authority of it ſufficiently enforced upon their hearers, or readers, if, keeping ſtill cloſe to the true meaning and intention thereof, they did not conſtantly render the very language of the Text, but ſometimes make uſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, though not diſagreeing, yet not the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, as we ſay, word for word.<note place="margin">D. de legib. l. <hi>Scire leges.</hi> &amp; l. 2. C. de Comm. legat.</note> For the great <hi>Lawyer</hi> tells us, <hi>Leges non ex verbis, ſed ex mente intelligendas.</hi> And if this will not be enough to render them excuſable, the very <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> themſelves, (examples fitteſt to follow, and ableſt, if any, to juſtifie,) in unqueſtioned writ have done the like, as both M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> hath well obſerved upon this Apoſtolicall Writer, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:160356:7"/> every one knowes who hath been but diligent to compare with the Old Teſtament places quoted thence into the New. They did likewiſe, not without the ſame warrant, to make up one perfect ſenſe, or period, collect, and heap together pieces or portions taken from ſeverall places and paſſages of Scripture, as if they had been there joyned together, and followed one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And this our Lord <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf doth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Tell ye the daughter of</hi> Sion, <hi>Behold thy King cometh unto thee, meek, and ſitting upon an aſſe, and a colt, the foal of an aſſe.</hi> For the former words, <hi>Tell ye the daughter of</hi> Sion, are taken out of <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.11. what followes is to be found in <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9. To have noted thus much, will ſerve, as a ſufficient <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to prepare the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and leſs knowing Reader, and withall prevent his being troubled, if he find not all quotations, alleged heer in what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, juſt agreeing with thoſe <hi>Bibles,</hi> which we have commonly in our hands. And they that do not obſerve this,<note n="a" place="margin">Exerc. Sacr. lib. 3. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Fieri non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt quin impingant,</hi> ſaith the excellent <hi>Heinſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>VIII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>If thou offer aright, and doſt not divide aright,</hi> &amp;c.] They, that onely turn over the Engliſh Bibles, will the leſs wonder at this reading, when they ſhall underſtand, that not onely <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> with all the antienteſt <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of either language; but even the learned <hi>Jewes</hi> themſelves, which lived preſently after Chriſt, and at the time of the laſt Captivity, uſed for the moſt part that Greek Tranſlation, which is commonly called, <hi>The Septuagint,</hi> from whence this Text is taken. To inſtance in one or two places of an hundred: In the Goſpel, where it is ſaid, that Chriſt <hi>came to</hi> Nazareth, <hi>and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his custome went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and ſtood up to read; and that there being delivered to him the book of the Prophet</hi> Eſaias, <hi>he opened it, and found the place where it was written.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 4.18. Iſai. 61.1.</note> The ſpirit of the Lord is upon me, &amp;c. Theſe words, and what follow, <hi>Luke</hi> delivers to us according to the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> though it be moſt manifeſt Chriſt read them in the <hi>Ebrew;</hi> now that verſion, for what we read out of Ebrew <hi>[and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound]</hi> hath, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of ſight to the blind:</hi> to which <hi>Luke</hi> adds (as if it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) out of <hi>Chap.</hi> 58.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to let the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,</hi> or <hi>broken, go free.</hi> But you will ſay <hi>Luke</hi> was no <hi>Jew;</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:160356:7"/> therefore could not well interpret out of a language he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not. And we dare not peremptorily determine that every one that had the Spirit, had likewiſe the gift of languages. For <hi>Paul</hi> then, who was one, he in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> proving, againſt the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that were the Children of the <hi>Free-woman,</hi> and not of the <hi>Bond-woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.27.</note> cites a place out of the ſame Prophet, after his uſuall manner, according to the Seventies Gr. edition; as <hi>Hierom</hi> hath obſerved it. Nay,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.5.</note> being an <hi>Ebrew of the Ebrews,</hi> and writing to his own country-men (for he is verily thought the<note n="*" place="margin">Baron. ad An. <abbr>LX.</abbr> § 42. 43. &amp;c. vide Lamp. Alard. Epiphyl. lib. 1.</note> Autor) he doth exactly (whether he writ it in the <hi>Ebrew,</hi> or no,) follow<note n="†" place="margin">Hieron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Iſai. cap. 6.</note> the ſence and words of the very ſame Tranſlation; except any one can ſurmiſe, that his ſcribe, or Interpreter (be it whether it will be) durſt be ſo bold, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver that again according to the <abbr>LXX.</abbr> which himſelf had firſt conceived, and dictated, after the <hi>Ebrew verity. Sequutus eſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hujus epistolae</hi> 
               <abbr>LXX.</abbr> 
               <hi>Interpretum editionem,</hi> ſaith the all-knowing <hi>Joſeph Scaliger;</hi> The <hi>Author</hi> not <hi>Tranſlator:</hi> and there are other reaſons would make a man conjecture that it was ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally Greek. Though not in this perhaps, yet in many other things of this kind antiquity hath fouly impoſed upon our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. However, certain it is, that two of <hi>Paul</hi>'s own country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the learnedeſt of the Nation after him, the one <hi>Philo,</hi> eſteemed by antiquity the <hi>Plato</hi> of the Jewes; the other <hi>Joſephus,</hi> a <hi>Phariſee</hi> by his own report; whom though I will not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with <hi>Paul</hi> for exactneſs of obſervance in his ſect, (which himſelf ſticks not to make boaſt of, even after his converſion,<note place="margin">Act. 22.3.26.5.</note>) yet undoubtedly was he moſt exact, as well in the Language, as lawes of his own people: Notwithſtanding that, both theſe are obſerved to make uſe of this verſion of the 70. Elders, rather then themſelves to interpret out of their own Books, and Language, (which they were moſt abſolutely able to do, it being native to them; and their Gr. onely acquired by ſtudy,) as often as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion offered it ſelf.<note place="margin">Praefat. ad <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; contra Appi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. lib 1.</note> And indeed it is to be wondred at in <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> that he ſhould ſo do; eſpecially in a matter of that moment, as the computation of the yeares from the Creation, in which he makes choice to follow the Seventies account, which indeed as far diſagrees with the <hi>Ebrew</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Videſis Mich. Glycam An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. part 2.</note>, as the <hi>Samaritan</hi> comes not neer either of them. And whether <hi>Nennius,</hi> the old Britain,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:160356:8"/> follow him,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Brito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. cap. 1.</note> in his Tranſlation by <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> in reckoning the ſame yeares, or elſe the old <hi>Latin Tranſlation</hi> out of the Seventy, is a queſtion needs not heer much to trouble us. Now all this is ſaid, not with any intent to prefer the <hi>broken cisterns</hi> of Tranſlations, before the <hi>fountain of living waters</hi> contained in the Originall Ebrew: but to ſhew in what eſteem, and how gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received the Seventies Edition was in the Apoſtles age, and thoſe next following: and we muſt needs ſay with <hi>Jerom;</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ep. ad Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſ. in 4. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. <hi>Illa vera interpretatio, quam Apoſtoli probaverunt.</hi> v. ejus praef. in J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rem.</note> that <hi>that is a true Tranſlation which the Apoſtles approved of:</hi> Onely it were to be wiſhed, we had it now in that <hi>purity,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Si <hi>70.</hi> Interp. pura, &amp; ut ab eis in Gr. verſa eſt editio perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neret, ſuper flue, mi <hi>Chromati,</hi> impelleres, ut Ebraea tibi v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Lat. ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. <hi>Hieron. prolog. in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralip.</hi>
               </note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Primitive Church enjoyed it: Of the reſtoring of which, in ſome good ſort, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> (a man born for publique good, and advancement of better literature,) hath given the Chriſtian learned world, not onely good hopes, but alſo ſome aſſurance. In the mean while, having it no better then we have, who can patiently bear with that too magiſterious cenſure<note n="*" place="margin">Rich. Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut. Ep. Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wic. Orig. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. tom. 1. part. poſter. § 54. p. 36.</note>, of one, who otherwiſe indeed had learning enough for two honeſt Biſhops: <hi>Magnam habere</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, <hi>debet interpretatio</hi> 70. <hi>&amp; in iis quae ad Christi condeſcenſionem</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; in carne ſuſceptâ</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ſpectant, majorem apud me habebit, quàm</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braica, <hi>quam tantopere quidam ampullantur, veritas, ut appellant.</hi> And yet he had told us not long before, that it was but a <hi>miſcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany verſion, non pura puta</hi> 70. <hi>ex</hi> Aquilae, Symmachi, <hi>aliorum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionibus conſtata.</hi> He was a man<note n="†" place="margin">J. S. de DIs Syr. Synt. 2. cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Graecè ſanè &amp; Latinè doctus;</hi> and of the two Languages, which it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to make uſe of, becoming an exquiſite Maſter in the one, <hi>contempſit alteram.</hi> As for this very Text,<note n="b" place="margin">De Geſtis Aelfredi R.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſerius Menevenſis</hi> (he was B<hi rend="sup">P</hi> of <hi>Sherborn</hi> about the year <abbr>DCCCLXXX.</abbr>) hath the reading of it after the Gr. of the 70. out of the ſame Latine verſion thereof before mentioned, and generally in uſe of old time in theſe Kingdomes, before the vulgar Latin came either to be admitted, or enforced: <hi>Si rectè offeras, rectè autem non dividas, peccas.</hi> And what follows heer in the next words; <hi>And</hi> Caïn <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Abel <hi>his brother, Let us go along into the field,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the ſame <abbr>LXX.</abbr> although it be wanting in the <hi>Ebrew,</hi> yet it is to be found in the <hi>Samaritan Pentateuch.</hi> Of which alſo<note n="a" place="margin">Quaeſt. Ebr. in <hi>Geneſim.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jerom</hi> took notice: <hi>Superfluum ergo eſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quod in Samaritanorum &amp; noſtro volumine reperitur, Tranſeamus in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:160356:8"/> Campum.</hi> See incomparable M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Selden praefat. ad Marmora Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delliana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aäron <hi>and</hi> Miriam <hi>had their habitation out of the Camp.</hi>]<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>IX.</abbr>
               </note> We muſt heer read <hi>Clement</hi> warily, and favourably. <hi>Aäron</hi> is not ſaid in the Text to be ſhut forth; but <hi>Miriam</hi> onely. Neither was their murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> the immediate cauſe thereof; for then had <hi>Aäron</hi> alſo been put out: But <hi>Miriam</hi>'s leproſie,<note place="margin">Levit. 13.46.</note> (according to the Law;) it being the particular and ſingle puniſhment inflicted upon her by God, and that for particular reaſons not heer to be diſcuſſed, for her <hi>ſpeaking</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes.</hi> See <hi>Deut.</hi> 
               <abbr>XXIV.</abbr> 9. But <hi>Clement</hi> may be excuſed by great examples. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us in his <abbr>I</abbr> to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> that Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.5.</note> after <hi>he roſe again, was ſeen of</hi> Cephas, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>then of the twelve.</hi> A perfect number for an imperfect. For indeed there were not at moſt above eight, if ſo many: <hi>Judas</hi> having hanged himſelf; <hi>Peter,</hi> with the beloved Diſciple, being abſent; as appeares by paſſages in <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Luke;</hi> Neither indeed was <hi>Thomas</hi> there.<note place="margin">Joh. 20.10. Luk. 24.34. Joh. 20.24.</note> And from <hi>Paul</hi>'s following words we may gather <hi>James</hi> was away too. Now theſe words are meant of his firſt appearance to his Diſciples. So that they, (and ſome of them are of the antients,) do nothing, who have mended the place, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>eleven,</hi>] when as neither ſo the account will ſtand good. Many ſuch inſtances may be brought alſo out of the moſt antient and beſt Heathen writers; but this is not a fit place for them. This ſhall be enough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He paſſed unto the due appointed place of Glory.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>X.</abbr>
               </note> Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Polycarpus</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians</hi> makes uſe of this expreſſion, (which he borrowes from <hi>Clement</hi>) concerning <hi>Paul</hi> and other holy men; onely the <hi>Verb</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is from this place to be reſtored thither<note n="*" place="margin">Patr. Junius Not. Critic. in Polycar. Ep. <hi>Oxon.</hi> edit. à <hi>Dn. Uſſerio.</hi> 1644.</note>: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. And the whole paſſage of that part thereof is tranſcribed by <hi>Euſebius.</hi> But in this mentioning of <hi>Peter</hi> heer, there is nothing of his Prerogative and Primacy;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nothing of his univerſall Epiſcopacy, and unlimited Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bequeathed to his Succeſſors; no not any thing of his own being Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> or appointing <hi>Clement</hi> after him to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in a ſingle prelaticall power above the other <hi>Preſbyters.</hi> Not a word of all this in him, from whom, had there been ever
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:160356:9"/> any ſuch thing, we might beſt expect it. Nay his very being at <hi>Rome,</hi> whether ever at all, or no, is queſtioned, I and denied too, by men of unqueſtionable learning,<note n="†" place="margin">Tract. ſuper eâ re apud <hi>Melch. Goldaſt.</hi> Tom. 3. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. Rom. Imperii.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lricus Velenus, Math. Fl. Illyricus, Dav. Pareus, Joſ. Scaliger, Sibrandus, Salmaſius,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others. And indeed that he never ſaw <hi>Rome,</hi> for about ſome <abbr>XX.</abbr> years next after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by very evident places of Holy Scripture: where notwithſtanding they will have him to be crucified about ſome <abbr>XXXVII.</abbr> years after that time; having ſate Biſhop there above <abbr>XXV.</abbr> of them, and <abbr>VII.</abbr> more before that at <hi>Antioch.</hi> This, I ſay, if we prove, that <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo far from being at <hi>Rome</hi> for the firſt <abbr>XX.</abbr> years, (and we will ſee what may be done afterward for the other <abbr>XVII.</abbr>) that indeed he was at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or in places a great deal more remote then it, in the Eaſt for all that while, we ſhall wondrouſly trouble their account, and indeed ſhake the whole foundation and fabrique of their ill-contrived <hi>Roman</hi> Eccleſiaſticall Monarchy, which they pretend to derive, (but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on moſt uncertain proofs,) from <hi>Peter</hi>'s reſidence, and juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, there. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And thus we doe it.</p>
            <p>For the <abbr>I.</abbr> year after the Aſcenſion, <hi>Peter</hi> preached <hi>daily</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> either <hi>in the Temple,</hi> or <hi>in</hi> private <hi>houſes,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his former impriſonment, and the Order of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel to the contrary. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.42. After the Martyrdom of <hi>Stephan,</hi> which happened in the <abbr>II.</abbr>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Baron. ad An. <abbr>XXIV.</abbr> § 301.</note> year after the Aſcenſion, he was ſent with <hi>John</hi> to them of <hi>Samaria,</hi> whence <hi>he returned to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Act.</hi> 8.14.25. The <abbr>IV.</abbr> or perhaps the <abbr>V.</abbr> year, and the third after his own converſion, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſees him at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and ſtaies with him 15. daies. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.18. The ſixt year after he cures <hi>Aeneas</hi> of the palſey at <hi>Lydda,</hi> and from thence goes to <hi>Joppa,</hi> where <hi>he tarried many dayes. Act.</hi> 9.34.43. The <abbr>VII.</abbr> year he baptizes <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centurion at <hi>Ceſarea. Act.</hi> 10.48. where he <hi>tarried certain dayes;</hi> and returning to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he is found fault with for <hi>going out to men uncircumciſed,</hi> that is, the <hi>Gentiles. Act.</hi> 11.3. And upon this check received, it appeares by <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.8. that he meddled not any more with the Gentiles, but effectually laboring in his Miniſtry to the Circumciſion, as is moſt likely, he ſtaid thereabout till the <abbr>XI.</abbr> year, in which he was impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Herod,</hi> and miraculouſly freed, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.4. And this is the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:160356:9"/> time ſay ſome he went to <hi>Rome.</hi> But they ſay it onely. Beſides, how can this agree with his ſitting at <hi>Antioch</hi> 
               <abbr>VII.</abbr> years before his coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> which they tell us of? Now he hath not been at <hi>Antioch</hi> yet, nor will not be till anon. And we find him again at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> For the <abbr>XIV<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </abbr> year after S. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſeen him at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> (before mentioned,) which makes the<note n="b" place="margin">v. Hieron. in <abbr>II.</abbr> ad Gal.</note> 
               <abbr>XVIII<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </abbr> after Chriſt's Aſcenſion, and in the <abbr>IX.</abbr> year of <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> he meets with him again in the ſame place, and leaves him to the Circumciſion, himſelf and <hi>Barnabas</hi> departing to the Gentiles, according to an agreement made among them. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. Which agreement being put into their hearts, without all doubt, immediately by the Holy Spirit, as being Preſident of their Councel, we cannot piouſly, or with Charity, imagine, that <hi>Peter</hi> would break the Order thereof, or ſo much as a compact agreed upon among themſelves; eſpecially if we conſider how wary he muſt needs be in dealing with the Gentiles, by reaſon of the fear he ſtood in of them, who were of the Circumciſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.12. and to the miniſtry of whom he was deputed by the Spirit, not onely at this Aſſembly; but formerly alſo: for his was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Apoſtleſhip of the Circumciſion, Gal.</hi> 2.8. Well; after this Councel, held, as is ſaid, about eighteen years after Chriſt's Aſcenſion, <hi>Paul</hi> meets him yet again, (it is not very likely it ſhould be preſently after,) and that at <hi>Antioch,</hi> far enough out of the way from <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he <hi>withſtands him to his face,</hi> and frights him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meddling any more with the Gentiles, as being wholly contrary to their compact and agreement. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. From hence he <hi>withdraws and ſeparates himſelf. Gal.</hi> 2.12. But whither goes he? To the <hi>Jewes,</hi> or Chriſtians, in <hi>Rome?</hi> At this time there were none to be found there. <hi>Oroſius</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Oroſ. lib. 7. c. 6.</note> out of <hi>Joſephus:</hi> Claudii <hi>anno nono expulſos <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe</hi> Judaeos, <hi>refert</hi> Joſephus. Suetonius:<note n="d" place="margin">In <hi>Claudio,</hi> cap. 25.</note> Judaeos <hi>impulſore</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Christ.</hi> So cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Heathen.</note> Chreſto <hi>aſſiduè tumultuantes</hi> Româ <hi>expulit. Claudius</hi> had ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed thence all the <hi>Jews,</hi> before <hi>Peter</hi> could get thither; that is the <hi>Christians</hi> aſwel:<note n="†" place="margin">Adi Arrian. in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 2. cap. 9. <hi>parùm heic in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectum ab Interprete.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.1.</note> for as yet they were not ſo quite diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminated by the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſo that <hi>Oroſius</hi> needed not ſo much to have troubled himſelf about this place of <hi>Suetonius.</hi> Moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he went then to <hi>the ſtrangers ſcattered in</hi> Aſia. &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. whoſe Metropolis was <hi>Babylon,</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:160356:10"/> from whence he wrote his Firſt Epiſtle. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.13. <hi>The Church which is at Babylon elected together with you ſaluteth you.</hi> That <hi>Babylon</hi> heer is meant of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is not <hi>Euſebius</hi> out of fancifull <hi>Papias,</hi> or <hi>Jerom</hi> out of him, that can perſwade us without bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſons.<note place="margin">Ad An. <abbr>XLV.</abbr> § 17. <hi>Nec me imprudenter dicturum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimo.</hi> &amp;c.</note> For the conceit indeed of <hi>Baronius,</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould give a falſe name to the place, becauſe he would not be found out where he was, truly it is not altogether irridiculous; though himſelf thinks he ſpeaks <hi>ſomewhat prudently</hi> therein. We know the difference between <hi>Epistolicall,</hi> and <hi>Propheticall,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; and confeſs we deſerve to be laugh'd at, if we ſhould beleeve him, that it was uſuall with the Apoſtles, to change mens names, aſwell as the names of places, for particular ends and advantages; as we have ſeen the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> do with us, the <hi>Cardinals</hi> very friends, and greateſt Champions for <hi>Peters</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy at <hi>Rome.</hi> By this time it appeares to every ingenuous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that will not ſuffer it ſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be led by the noſe by whatever authority it is, which can but plead an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, that <hi>Peter for ſome</hi> 
               <abbr>XX.</abbr> 
               <hi>years after Chriſts Aſcenſion never ſo much as ſaw</hi> Rome. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quod erat demonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now ſpeak to the other <abbr>XVII.</abbr> years.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen, that during the Reign of <hi>Tiberius, Caligula,</hi> and even unto the end of <hi>Claudius, Peter</hi> hath never been at <hi>Rome. Nero</hi> is next. Let us hear what the great<note n="e" place="margin">Joſ. Scalig. ad Joan <abbr>XVIII.</abbr> com. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Amender of times</hi> will ſay: <hi>A Chriſti in coelum receptu ad</hi> 
               <abbr>IV.</abbr> 
               <hi>annum</hi> Neronis <hi>certo certius eſt</hi> Petrum Romam <hi>non veniſſe.</hi> You hear how perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he is. He tells us <hi>certainty it ſelf is not more certain,</hi> then that <hi>Peter</hi> never came to <hi>Rome</hi> before the <abbr>IIII.</abbr> year of <hi>Nero.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did after that, or no, remaines to be examined. About the end of <hi>Claudius,</hi> or at leaſt the beginning of <hi>Nero,</hi> as is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally beleeved, ſome two or three years before his own coming thither, <hi>Paul</hi> writes his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> though <hi>Pareus</hi> would have it later. In the laſt Chapter thereof he ſalutes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides others, by name neer upon thirty<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 16.2.</note> Saints, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of that Church. Now <hi>res ipſa clamat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Inſtitut. cap. 8. § 101.</note> 
               <hi>non debuiſſe Petrum praeteriri ſi Romae fuiſſet.</hi> Not Chriſtian charity, but common ingenuity may wonder, that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, had he been at <hi>Rome. Tantaene animis coeleſtibus irae?</hi> So
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:160356:10"/> fervent ſure was S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s love to all the Saints, that he could by no meanes neglect, much leſs hate, him whom he had once thought worthy of his chiding, and reproof, at <hi>Antioch.</hi> Or had he left <hi>Rome</hi> by reaſon or the <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Claudius,</hi> as <hi>Baronius</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ad An. <abbr>LVIII.</abbr> § 51.</note> pretends, but having no Teſtimony in the world for it, (and yet this is all the reaſons he allegeth for <hi>Paul</hi>'s not naming him, though he makes ſhew of more,) ſo great a light of the Church being miſſing from his own Orb, might have ſeemed worthy of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s enquiring after; eſpecially writing to the place where he is conceived to have had ſuch power and preëmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. But ſome few yeares after <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf comes to <hi>Rome.</hi> There was ſtore then of <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in the City. Doth he then finde <hi>Peter</hi> returned? No ſuch matter ſet down by him that tells us the ſtory; and it is not probable that <hi>Peter</hi>'s name at leaſt, in caſe he were come back to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould have wanted ſetting down by him, that was otherwiſe very ſtudious of his actions; and who tels us that many others reſorted unto <hi>Paul,</hi> while he <hi>dwelt in his own hired houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 28.30.</note> for the ſpace <hi>of two whole years</hi> together. None, no not any the leaſt mention neither of his being at <hi>Rome,</hi> is to be found in thoſe many Epiſtles written there by <hi>Paul,</hi> to the <hi>Galatians, Epheſians, Philippians, Coloſſians, Timothy, Philemon,</hi> after his long continuance in that place. He acquaints the<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 1.18.2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Galatians</hi> with his ſeeing him at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Antioch:</hi> and could no accident happen at <hi>Rome,</hi> that might miniſter him occaſion to mention his ſeeing him there, (if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance he did ſo) in his Letters to none of the Churches? He gives teſtimony to the <hi>Philippians</hi> concerning this <hi>Clement,</hi> then with him in <hi>Rome</hi> when he wrote his<note n="†" place="margin">Phil. 4.3.</note> Epiſtle to them; and would he ſay nothing of <hi>Peter,</hi> by whom they will needs have <hi>Clement</hi> conſtituted to be his ſucceſſour in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Rome?</hi> He tels the ſame <hi>Philippians,</hi> he had none with him ſo equally affected like himſelf as was <hi>Timothy</hi> for their good, all <hi>others ſeeking their own, not the things which are Jeſus Christs.</hi> Can this aſperſion light upon <hi>Peter?</hi> Can <hi>Timothy,</hi> but a ſon of <hi>Paul</hi>'s nurtering, and a meer novice in compariſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> have a greater care of the people of Chriſt, then he that forſooth muſt be Univerſall Biſhop of all the Churches? S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels the ſame <hi>Timothy,</hi> that <hi>at his firſt anſwer at</hi> Rome <hi>none ſtood with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.16.</note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:160356:11"/> 
               <hi>but all men forſook him.</hi> High ſhame for <hi>Peter,</hi> if ſo be he were then at <hi>Rome!</hi> Nay, in the ſame Epiſtle (which they tell us was written in the laſt<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Henr. Bunting.</hi> Chron. Eccleſ. &amp;c. 2 Tim. 4.6.7.8.10.12.11.</note> year of <hi>Nero,</hi> and is that of both their Martyrdoms,) S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſignifying unto him, with a prophetique ſpirit no doubt, his <hi>departure being at hand, the finiſhing of his cours, and the obtaining of a Crown;</hi> he acquaints him withall what way <hi>Demas,</hi> and <hi>Creſcens,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and <hi>Tychicus</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: And out of a conſideration of his own ſolitude, he lets him know moreover that of all the Miniſters of the Goſpel <hi>Luke onely was with him.</hi> And was not <hi>Peter</hi>'s errand whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever worthy the giving <hi>Timothy</hi> notice of? Or if they, whom he names, were all, who had departed from him, what becomes of <hi>Peter</hi> then, when <hi>Luke</hi> alone is found remaining? Where now ſhall we find <hi>Peter</hi> in the time of <hi>Nero?</hi> or where hath he beſtowed himſelf?<note n="k" place="margin">Menander in <hi>Hypobolimaeo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I like not theſe ſtragling gods,</hi> ſaid the Comedian of old. A Biſhop never reſident; never at home in his own Dioceſs; but alwayes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.15.</note> quite contrary to his own rule and precept? An il preſident ſure, and example, to the Biſhops of after ages; and too much (the whole world is witneſs) imitated, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But though we cannot find him alive, and exerciſing his Juriſdiction, in this great City, the <hi>publique</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleot. Junior. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Star of the whole Earth,</hi> ſhall we find him dead there? Neither doth that ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appeare. Certainly a moſt ſtrange fate, that the manner of his ſuffring (<hi>Joh.</hi> 21.18.) ſhould have clearer teſtimony given of it, then the place where! The underſtanding Reader by this time cannot be ignorant, why we have ſo vehement a ſuſpicion of the truth of that common relation concerning <hi>Peter</hi> and his martyrdome at <hi>Rome.</hi> What is to be done then? To forſake ſlight, and, as is manifeſt, forged authorities, and in ſtead of them to fly to conjectures, will afford us but ſmall help for the finding out of the truth. And yet me thinks <hi>Peter</hi>'s writing of his Epiſtle from <hi>Babylon</hi> ſeems to me to confirme that moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable one of <hi>Scaliger,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Scal. d. l.</note> who thinks he rather ſuffred under ſome <hi>Provinciall Magiſtrate</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Aſiae, where he preached to the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſcattered far and wide in <hi>Pontus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Bithynia.</hi> However his argument out of <hi>Tacitus</hi> is not good to prove that he was not <hi>crucified</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> under
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:160356:11"/> 
               <hi>Nero,</hi> becauſe, ſaies he, in that onely Perſecution under him, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were burnt in publique, wrapt up in ſear-cloth with pitch and other combuſtible ſtuff, being tyed upright by the necks to a ſtake, and all this to give light to his night paſtimes and ſports; when as <hi>Tacitus</hi> indeed as well confeſſeth that ſome were <hi>crucified,</hi> and alſo wurried to death in beaſts skins by dogs.<note n="n" place="margin">Tacit. Annal. lib. <abbr>XV.</abbr>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pereuntibus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>addita ludibria, ut ferarum tergis contecti laniatu canum interirent, aut crucibus affixi; aut flammandi, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ubi defeciſſet dies in uſum nocturni luminis urerentur.</hi> To ſay no more; the reſolution of <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſpeaking of this ſame buſineſs, is very grave, and moderate:<note n="o" place="margin">Inſtit. c. <abbr>VIII.</abbr> § 102.</note> 
               <hi>Res illius temporis ita ſunt opinionum varietate implicitae, ut non temere adhibenda ſit fides, ubi aliquid ſcriptum legimus. Et tamen propter hunc ſcripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conſenſum, non pugno quin illic mortuus fuerit: ſed Epiſcopum fuiſſe, praeſertim longo tempore, perſuaderi nequeo.</hi> And the truth is, that the Chriſtians of the more antient Ages, perceiving a great flaw or defect in the Hiſtory of Church affaires from the end of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles</hi> to <hi>Trajan</hi>'s time, took upon them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with no bad intent, to make up, with ſupplement of their own pure invention, that <hi>Chaſm,</hi> or breach in the Story: Herein, as none of the worſt parcels, I mean, (as it hapned out,) not of the leaſt advantage to after times, was <hi>Peter</hi>'s coming to Rome, his Epiſcopacy there, with his Martyrdome, and Succeſſors. They had read perhaps in<note n="p" place="margin">d. l.</note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> or <hi>Suetonius</hi> of the perſecution of Chriſtians under <hi>Nero,</hi> which was indeed the firſt,<note n="q" place="margin">In <hi>Ner.</hi> c. 16. Id. in <hi>Claud.</hi> c. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Claudius</hi> onely baniſhing them the City as is aforeſaid: Hence they ſtrait made a conjecture that <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> might then ſuffer; though truly they kept no exact obſervation of the time.</p>
            <p>But that this indeed could not be ſo, if it hath not already been ſufficiently proved, let us hear what <hi>Eutychius</hi> the Patriarch of the Orthodox Chriſtians at <hi>Alexandria</hi> telleth us, a writer, who for his Age and Authority may very well be heard, and in whoſe late publiſhed<note n="b" place="margin">Arabicè edit. à Clariſs. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deno.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antiquities</hi> of his own Church you may read; <hi>Occiſus est Petrus ſub annum</hi> 
               <abbr>XXII.</abbr> 
               <hi>poſt Dominum noſtrum Christum,</hi> which falling in with the beginning of <hi>Nero,</hi> how could <hi>Peter</hi> ſuffer in the <hi>Perſecution</hi> begun by <hi>Nero</hi> ſo long after, as he is ſaid in the common account? Notwithſtanding, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the commonly received tradition of <hi>Peter</hi>'s being at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:160356:12"/> and that there forſooth he writ <hi>Evangelium Marci, cum Marco, lingua</hi>
               <note n="⸫" place="margin">i. <hi>Graecâ,</hi> ita Arabib. dicta. v. <hi>Selden.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Romana.</hi> Yet he acknowledgeth him not to have been ever Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> but ſaies plainly that <hi>Linus erat primus Patriarcha Romanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſuffred under ſome <hi>Provinciall Magiſtrate,</hi> and not at <hi>Rome</hi> by the command of <hi>Nero,</hi> I could ſuffer my ſelf eaſily to be brought to beleeve, by reaſon of theſe words of <hi>Clement</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>under the Governours,</hi> whether <hi>Preſidiall,</hi> or <hi>Proconſular,</hi> I know no more, then I am determined to ſtrive againſt the violent current of all antiquity. For I know how impatiently the ulcers of inveterate errors ſuffer themſelvs to be handled, and ſearched into.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XI.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>And made his way to the utmost bounds of the Weſt.]</hi> Doth he heer mean his going into <hi>Spain,</hi> his reſolution for which jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney himſelf hath ſet down in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> in theſe words? <hi>Whenſoever I take my journey into Spain, I will come to you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <abbr>XV.</abbr> 24.28.</note> 
               <hi>for I truſt to ſee you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you</hi> and a little after. <hi>When therefore I have perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this and have ſealed to them this fruit, I will come by you into Spain.</hi> Which whether he ever performed hath hitherto been diſputed: This place of <hi>Clement</hi> ſeems much to confirm that he did. Some very learned Papiſts would utterly deny it, as<note n="a" place="margin">Ep. ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſt. 11. cap. <hi>Quis neſciat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> P.<note n="b" place="margin">In Rom. c. 15. (ex <hi>Gelaſio</hi> apud Grat. diſt. 22. q. 2. cap. <hi>Beatus.</hi>)</note> 
               <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">In Rom. c. 15. ad l.</note> 
               <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ad An. <abbr>LXI.</abbr> § 2.3. &amp;c.</note> inclines to beleeve it; in whom you may finde the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies for it collected out of the Gr. and Lat. Fathers, among whom <hi>Theodoret</hi> tells us, (though this place be omitted by the <hi>Cardinal</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">In Ep. ad Rom. cap. 15. ad l.</note> 
               <hi>ſpiritu prophetico eam profectionem praedictam, &amp; idcirco neceſſariò implendam fuiſſe.</hi> Nay, he goes farther, and ſaies;<note n="f" place="margin">In Pſal. 116.</note> 
               <hi>In Hiſpanias pervenit, &amp; inſulis quae in mari jacent utilitatem attulit;</hi> in which place by his <hi>[Inſulae in mari]</hi> he underſtands undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly the <hi>Britannies;</hi> as he ſeems to interpret himſelf<note n="g" place="margin">De Car. Graec. affect. lib. <abbr>IX.</abbr>
               </note> elſwhere, telling us that among others, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he meanes <hi>Paul,</hi> did perſwade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Britains and Gauls, as well as other Nations, <hi>to receive the Laws of Christ crucified.</hi> And for farther witneſs, the very ſame is affirmed by <hi>Sophronius</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Serm. de Natal. Apoſt.</note>, the Patriarch of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> (not he whoſe ſpurious, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit book we have inſcrib'd <hi>Fragment. Peregrin. Petri &amp; Pauli,</hi>) and by <hi>Venantius</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">De vitâ <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini.</hi> lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> a very antient Chriſtian Poët, whoſe is this:
<q>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:160356:12"/>
                  <l>Tranſiit Oceanum, vel quà facit inſula portum;</l>
                  <l>Quaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Britannus habet terras, quaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ultima Thule.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay his teſtimony is in verſe; I ſay little to that: But dare be confident that that is but Poëtry, or making, which the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rob. Perſon.</hi> de 3<hi rend="sup">b</hi>. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Angliae part. 1. cap. § 21. <hi>Rich. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ch.</hi> hiſt. Brit. lib 4. <hi>Jo. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. de reb. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicis. Praefat. de Antiq. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Brytan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicae. &amp;c.</note> Papiſts, our countrymen, would delude us with about <hi>Peter</hi>'s being heer, his <hi>conſtituting Churches, and ordaining Biſhops, Preſbyters, and Deacons</hi> among us; (for they would have little good done any where but by him;) and all this upon very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, or to ſpeake better, upon falſe and forged authorities. For as for<note n="l" place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 2. ca. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Nicephorus Calliſtus,</hi> their beſt Author, neither he, <hi>Niceph. Gregoras</hi> or any other of the name, are of any antiquity almoſt to ſpeak of beyond yeſterday; therefore not to be credited in a buſineſs of this kind: and <hi>Baronius</hi> himſelf confeſſeth, that this is delivered<note n="m" place="margin">Ad An. <abbr>XLIV.</abbr> § 38.</note> 
               <hi>abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliquo antiquorum teſtimonio.</hi> For <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">In Synopſi.</note>, the writing, which beares his name,<note n="*" place="margin">Salm. de Ep. &amp; Presbyt. Rivet. Crit. Sacri lib 3. ca. 13. Rob. Cocus Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. p. 115.</note> is moſt certainly ſuppoſititious. And their third man is the very <hi>Jacobus de Vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine,</hi> or if I could ſay worſe, of the Greek Church: I mean<note n="o" place="margin">Sym. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph. ad diem <abbr>XXIX.</abbr> 
                  <hi>Junii.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Symeon Metaphrastes,</hi> who whereas he cites <hi>Euſebius</hi> for what he ſaies, I am afraid he doth but put a falſe die upon us. No ſuch thing appears in his Hiſtory of the Church, where it ſhould be found, as in its moſt convenient place: if it were in ſome part of him, which is not come to our hands, we can ſay nothing to that, but, <hi>Quod perîſſe videmus, perditum ducimus.</hi> Theſe are all. Yet we could help them to a fourth man, my Lord of <hi>Arundel</hi>'s Gr. Anon. MS.<note n="p" place="margin">Apud Dn. Junium in Not. ad Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> of the <hi>Travels of Peter and Paul:</hi> I might have thought him the forged <hi>Sophronius</hi> before mentioned, but that I ſee him to be but a gleaner at beſt out of <hi>Symeon the Tranſlater:</hi> and in this buſineſs of <hi>Peter</hi>'s being in Britain he is tranſcribed by him <hi>verbatim.</hi> Let who ſo will ſee for better ſatisfaction <hi>Fran. Goodwin, de Converſ. Britan. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>D. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſer. de Britan. Eccleſiar. Primordiis, cap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>Jerom</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Catal. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptor. Eccl. in <hi>PAULO.</hi>
               </note> (who tranſlated this Epiſtle into Latin above <abbr>CC.</abbr> years ago) ſeems to have had this place of <hi>Clement</hi> in his mind, when he wrote theſe words of <hi>Paul: Evangelium Chriſti in Occidentis quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> partibus praedicavit;</hi> which, ſaies he, he did after his firſt diſmiſſion obtained at <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Nero;</hi> whereof himſelf makes mention <abbr>II</abbr> 
               <hi>Tim.</hi> 
               <abbr>IV.</abbr> 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repent ye houſe of</hi> Iſrael, &amp;c.] See M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi>'s Notes <hi>ad pag.</hi> 11.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XII.</abbr>
               </note> 
               <hi>edit. Graecolat.</hi> and what is obſerved heer <hi>Num.</hi> 
               <abbr>VII.</abbr> and <abbr>IIX.</abbr> of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:160356:13"/> the joyning of many places of Scripture into one ſenſe, or period; and of the differing readings from our ordinary <hi>Bibles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XIII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Let us faſten our contemplation,</hi> &amp;c.] This paſſage, and thoſe that follow, are tranſcribed hence by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his 4. <hi>Stromat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XIV.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Preached the instauration of all things to the World.]</hi> He meanes the reſtitution of what periſhed in the <hi>Flood,</hi> by the encreaſe of thoſe creatures, which in the following words he tels us God ſaved in the Ark. Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The word is uſed in <hi>Matthew</hi> for the ſecond coming of Chriſt in his Kingdome and power to judge the world,<note place="margin">Matth. 19.28.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.5.</note> when <hi>he ſhall make all things new.</hi> For <hi>Matthew</hi>'s language <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is expreſſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.30.</note> ſpeaking of the ſame promiſe of Chriſt to his Diſciples, that they ſhould then ſit upon <abbr>XII.</abbr> Thrones judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <abbr>XII.</abbr> Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But later Chriſtian Writers of the Gr. Church take it, ſome for the generall <hi>Reſurrection</hi> at the laſt day; others for <hi>Regeneration,</hi> or the New birth which is by Baptiſm. It is needleſs to heap hither their autorities.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XV.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Pillar of ſalt,</hi> remaining <hi>even unto this day.</hi>] Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Joſephus</hi> witneſſeth as much, who moreover tels us, that he ſaw it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>But</hi> Lot<hi>'s wife, as they retired thence, looking back towards the City, and more curiouſly beholding the deſtruction thereof, contrary to the Commandment of God, was transformed into a pillar of ſalt, which I have ſeen; for it remaineth even untill this day.</hi> Now <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Joſephus</hi> were <hi>Synchroni. Tertullian</hi> witneſſeth it was to be ſeen in his time; that is, not an hundred and fifty years after them. Which we may the leſs wonder at, when as beſides <hi>Burchardus,</hi> and divers others, our late <hi>Engliſh</hi> Travellers into thoſe parts affirme that it is ſtill undiſſolv'd, and ſtanding. <hi>Sulpicius Severus</hi> 300. years after <hi>Clement,</hi> calls this Pillar onely <hi>molem</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Hiſt. ſacr. l. 1.</note>, omitting to ſet down both the form, and ſubſtance or matter it conſiſted of. But his, not omiſſions onely, but manifeſt departing from the exact ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Holy Text, may frequently be obſerved. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he tels the ſtory hanſomly, and like himſelf: <hi>Sed mulier parùm dicto audiens, (humano malo quo agriùs vetitis abſtinetur,) reflexit oculos, ſtatim<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in molem converſa traditur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:160356:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Be ye mercifull, that ye may obtain mercy.]</hi> CLEMENT'S Gr.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XVI.</abbr>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Luke</hi>'s Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But ſee once for all <hi>N.</hi> 
               <abbr>VII.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Although he could do all things.]</hi> Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XVII.</abbr>
               </note> as is before obſerved, turn'd this Epiſtle into <hi>Latin,</hi> which we may fear is now quite loſt. His copy ſeems to have had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, miſſing heer; reading it thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he tranſlates this period, yet to be found in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings upon the <abbr>LII.</abbr> Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Eſay. Sceptrum Dei Dominus Jeſus Christus, non venit in jactantiâ ſuperbiae, cum poſſit omnia, ſed in humilitate.</hi> I have followed him. It is far the more cleare reading; yet <hi>Jerom</hi> doth not render <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Christ the ſcepter of the majesty of God:</hi> I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were wanting in his book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe he hath a mind to him.]</hi> Or, <hi>Becauſe he delighteth in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XVIII.</abbr>
               </note> Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. With this very paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, taken out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <abbr>XXII.</abbr> the Chief Prieſts and Elders mock't Chriſt upon the Croſs. <hi>Matth.</hi> 
               <abbr>XXVII.</abbr> 43. where alſo it would be better rendred, <hi>if he take delight in him,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] then as it is in our Bibles, (ſeeming rather tranſcribed from our Engliſh <hi>Reading</hi> Pſalms, as they call them, out of the <hi>Vulgar Latin, [quoniam vult eum,]</hi> then tranſlated out of the Gr.) <hi>if he will have him.</hi> The ſame Interpreter in this place of <hi>Matthew</hi> ſeems to have read, or at leaſt, to have underſtood the Gr. thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. for he tranſlates it: <hi>liberet nunc eum, ſi vult.</hi> omitting the former <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then miſpointing the words. And ſo quite alters the meaning. The Ebrew word ſignifieth indeed the ſame that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth, as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which occaſioned the <abbr>LXX.</abbr> to turn this place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And it is formerly obſerved, how generally they were followed. Otherwiſe <hi>Matthew,</hi> expreſſing the very ſame thing and ſence elſwhere in his own words, uſeth the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> or, <hi>delighted.</hi> And though the Vulgar heer in this <hi>Pſal.</hi> agree with the 70. yet in other places he leaves them, and comes neerer the ſignification of this later verb in rendring the Originall word. For whereas they have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.22. 2 Sam. 15.26.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. that Interpreter hath <hi>places Regi,</hi> and <hi>non places.</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:160356:14"/> But it may be gathered from the preface to this verſion of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or former edition, was tranſlated but out of the 70. onely heer and there amended by comparing it with the Ebrew Text afterward.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XIX.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>I am as the reaking of a pot.]</hi> The learned <hi>Publiſher</hi> of this Epiſtle, finding this place no where in the <hi>Pentateuch,</hi> or five books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> under whoſe name notwithſtanding it is heer cited, refers us to a very antient Gr.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſephus,</hi> ſive <hi>Joſippus,</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptor Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. v. <hi>James</hi> in Eclog. Bibl. Publ. Canta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brig. n. 243. &amp; Cl. <hi>Selden.</hi> de Anno Civili Judaeor. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 43.</note> Author, not yet ſet forth; (whom, with many<note n="†" place="margin">Alioſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os Graecos non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum editos; quos parum vexari ab iis puto qui in illis Collegiis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt: A me cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè non rarò re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſerentur, ſi ibi adeſſem. <hi>Joſ. Scalig. Ep. 234. ad Ri. Thompſ. de Biblioth. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae.</hi>
               </note> others, that have not ſeen the publique ſince the admired benefit of Printing, he, with ſome few better ſouls, ſuffers not to ſleep, and gather duſt, in our Libraries, or rather <hi>Bibliotaphs,</hi> either through egregious lazineſs, or want of conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, and encouragement, I know not whether: but I am ſure to our no ſmall ſhame; they beyond the ſeas taking notice of it, and envying us ſuch treaſuries as we make no uſe of:) This Author in one<note n="*" place="margin">Quaeſt. <hi>ſeu</hi> cap. 120.</note> part of his work hath collected together thoſe places in the New Teſtament, which ſeem to be taken or quoted out of the Old, but appear not any where extant in thoſe books thereof, which it hath pleaſed God to continue to his Church. As for theſe words heer, <hi>Clement</hi> ſeems to have them out of the 119. <hi>Pſal. v.</hi> 83. naming <hi>Moſes</hi> for <hi>David,</hi> perhaps with the ſame liberty, that he ſees Chriſt uſe <hi>Joh.</hi> 
               <abbr>X.</abbr> 34. where he urging a place out of the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> calls them the <hi>Law,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Is it not written in your Law,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaid, Ye are Gods?</hi> And the people ſeeme to imitate him to his face doing the ſame in the Ch. next ſave one following, <hi>Joh.</hi> 
               <abbr>XII.</abbr> 34. <hi>The people anſwered him; We have heard out of the Law, That Chriſt abideth ever.</hi> Which words it is apparent are taken out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <abbr>CX.</abbr> 4. See alſo <hi>Joh.</hi> 
               <abbr>XV.</abbr> 25. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.19. So <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe terms the Prophecy of <hi>Eſay</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> too: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <abbr>XIV.</abbr> 21. <hi>In the</hi> Law <hi>it is written:</hi> now the place he intends is <hi>Eſay</hi> 28.11. It is worth looking upon the learned <hi>Heinſius</hi> his <hi>Sacred Meditat.</hi> on this place of <hi>Pauls.</hi> And from this unqueſtionable example and authority it is, that the Fathers many times by this word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Law,</hi> do underſtand the whole <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> And yet Chriſt ſeems plainly to divide it into the Law, Prophets, and Pſalms, as appeares by many places, but eſpecially <hi>Luke</hi> 
               <abbr>XXIV.</abbr> 44. <hi>All things muſt be fulfilled which were written in the</hi> Law of Moſes, <hi>and in the</hi> Prophets, <hi>and in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:160356:14"/> the</hi> Pſalms, <hi>concerning me.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and Fathers moſt an end, followed alſo this diſtinction. And the <hi>Jews</hi> divided it not much otherwiſe, as we may find in <hi>Jerom;</hi> After the <hi>Law,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſecundum</hi> Prophetarum <hi>ordinem faciunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In prol. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leato.</note> 
               <hi>Tertius ordo</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>poſſidet: Et primus liber incipit ab</hi> Job: <hi>ſecundus autem</hi> David, <hi>quem</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That unpaſſable</hi> Ocean.]<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XX.</abbr>
               </note> The learned Editioner by theſe words underſtands the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Ocean. Sure very rightly. For the very ſame, or like, expreſſions did the writers not onely about this age, but in the following alſo, uſe concerning it. To confirm this more then probable conjecture, take the paines to read theſe verſes,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ. Scaliger</hi> primus edidit in <hi>Catalect.</hi> &amp;c.</note> pen'd moſt certainly about <hi>Clement</hi>'s time; and they are of <hi>Claudius</hi> th' Emperours Expedition into the <hi>Iland:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ocëanus</hi> nunc terga dedit, <hi>nec pervius</hi> ulli</l>
                  <l>Caeſareos faſces, Imperium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tulit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Al.</hi> Semoto.</note>Semota, &amp; <hi>vaſto</hi> disjuncta Britannia <hi>ponto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cincta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>inacceſſis</hi> horrida <hi>littoribus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Quam pater <hi>invictis</hi> Nereus vallaverat <hi>undis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Quam <hi>fallax aeſtu</hi> circuit <hi>Ocëanus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Aſpice confundit populos <hi>impervia tellus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conjunctum eſt, quod adhuc <hi>Orbis, &amp; Orbis,</hi> erat.</l>
               </q> For two reaſons Antiquity conceited this Sea moſt dangerous, and <hi>unpaſſable.</hi> Firſt, for the great abundance of huge Sea-monſters beleeved to be bred therein; which not onely<note n="b" place="margin">Lib. 4. od. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Horace</hi> intimates in theſe words:
<q>
                  <l>—<hi>Belluoſus,</hi> qui remotis</l>
                  <l>Obstrepit <hi>Ocëanus</hi> Britannis;</l>
               </q> But <hi>Juvenal</hi> alſo in his <abbr>X.</abbr> Satyr,
<q>Quantò Delphinis <hi>Balaena Britannica</hi> major.</q> 
               <hi>Festus Avienus</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Oris Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritimis.</note>, who lived under <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and is mentioned with good credit by S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> borrows the former expreſſion, ſpeaking likewiſe of the Ocëan Sea;
<q>
                  <l>Non uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> navibus <hi>turbidum</hi> late <hi>fretum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Et <hi>belluoſi</hi> gurgitem <hi>Ocëani</hi> ſecant.</l>
               </q> And I may wel think both places were in his mind,<note n="d" place="margin">Jac. Syncer. Sannazar. Ecl. Piſcator. <abbr>V.</abbr>
               </note> who wrote that gallant verſe, (and ſuch are all his,)
<q>
                  <hi>Senſit</hi> Arar, <hi>ſenſere</hi> maris fera monſtra Britanni.</q>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:160356:15"/> A ſingular ornament indeed he was to the laſt Age, and antient poëtry it ſelf;<note n="e" place="margin">— Hic ille <hi>Maroni Synce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſâ proximus, ut tumulo. <hi>Petr. Bembus Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal.</hi>
               </note> who as he enjoyed, not onely the <hi>Dwelling,</hi> but the <hi>Muſe</hi> alſo, of the <hi>Prince</hi> of Poëts while he liv'd, ſo had he the happineſs after he was dead to lye neereſt to his <hi>Relics.</hi> The ſecond reaſon was, not onely unexpected Tempeſts and ſtorms ſuddenly ariſing thereon, but the unuſuall violence alſo of the <hi>Tides,</hi> which if we hear <hi>Pytheas</hi> of <hi>Marſeils</hi> in <hi>Plinie</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Natur. Hiſt. lib 2. ca. 97.</note>, (for <hi>Strabo</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Geogr. li. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> hath utterly exploded his credit in what he relates of the <hi>Britannies) make it ſwell fourſcore cubits higher then the land. Mare, attolli horrendis aestibus adſuetum.</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtor. lib. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Amm. Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſpeaking of it. <hi>Caeſar</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Com. de bel. Gallico, lib. 5.</note> himſelf had dear experience of the roughneſs of it, when he neer loſt his whole navy upon our coaſt.<note n="h" place="margin">Com. de bel. Gallico, lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Maximâ coörta tempeſtate, propè omnes naves afflictae, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in littus ejectae, quòd ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> anchorae, funeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſubſiſterent, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nautae, gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernatoreſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vim tempeſtatis pati poſſent.</hi> and he found to his charges, to uſe his own words a little further,<note n="i" place="margin">Ibid. lib. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Longè aliam eſſe navigationem in concluſo mari, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in vaſtiſſimo ac apertiſſimo</hi> Ocëano. And yet certainly the danger which he conceived, and fear'd might happen, either in or after his paſſage, made him very wary, and provident in making choice of a fit <hi>ſeaſon</hi> for it; which indeed<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Appian</hi> tels us he did. Neither did time, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of skill in Navigation, leſſen this fearfull apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with after ages concerning the certain perill and hazard which they underwent, that ſail'd this Sea. <hi>Baſil</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> calls it<note n="l" place="margin">Homil. 4. in Hexaëmeron.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> renders,<note n="m" place="margin">Lib. Hexam. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>magnum &amp; inauſum navigantibus, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> intentatum naut is mare, quod</hi> Britannias<note n="n" place="margin">Ocëanus <hi>barbaris flucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> fremens. Paulin. de eodem. vide Geograph. <hi>Nubienſem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>frementi includit aequore, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ulterior a &amp; ipſis fabulis inacceſſa ſecreta ſe porrigit. Libanius</hi> alſo the famous So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſt, and Maſter unto <hi>Julian</hi> called by ſome th' <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> living in the ſame Age with <hi>S. Baſil,</hi> and deſcribing with what jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Conſtantius</hi> th' Emperour croſs'd this Sea into <hi>Britain,</hi> he calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Panegyr. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantio.</note>, (the very word that <hi>Clement</hi> uſeth heer,) <hi>unpaſſable;</hi> eſteeming more danger to be in this paſſage, then in a <hi>Sea-fight</hi> elſwhere; and the performance thereof with ſafety to deſerve no leſs then a <hi>Tropee. Plus eſt tranſiſſe ad Britannos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hegeſippus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">De Excid. Hieroſolym.</note>, (not he whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> formerly cites,) <hi>quàm triumphaſſe de Britannis.</hi> And well might he think ſo, when as that ſtupid <hi>Caligula,</hi> affecting ſome great deſign againſt <hi>Britain,</hi> with an
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:160356:15"/> army, as appeares out of <hi>Dio,</hi> of 250000. fighting men, being come to the ſhore, durſt hardly look the <hi>Britiſh Neptune</hi> in the face, much leſs truſt him. Yet that he might not be ſaid to come ſo far to no purpoſe, himſelf, with ſome few more,<note place="margin">Dio, &amp; Aur. Victor. ex edit. A. Schotti.</note> lanches out in his Gally, but fear makes him inſtantly put in again. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to make ſomething of it, upon the ſounding of a charge, he commands his army, which ſtood in <hi>Battalia</hi> all the while upon the ſhore, to gather ſhel-fiſh, (for it was upon an Ebb,) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to fill <hi>galeas &amp; ſinus,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Sueton. in <hi>Caligula,</hi> ca. 46.</note> 
               <hi>Spolia</hi> Ocëani <hi>vocans,</hi> Capitolio, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latioque <hi>debita:</hi> calling them <hi>Spoiles of the Ocean due to the Capitol and Palace.</hi> The <hi>Bravado</hi> of <hi>Claudius,</hi> next after him, was not much more tolerable: For counting it not enough to triumph for reducing a ſmall part of the Iland, (which indeed he entred with ſome ſucceſs; but I remember not whether with any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the paſſage,) after his return, he caus'd to be placed upon the top of his <hi>Palace</hi> a <hi>Naval Crown,</hi> as if he had tamed and ſubjugated the <hi>Ocean,</hi> like another <hi>Xerxes,</hi> in deſpight of the power of God appearing in that fierce Element; for which he is deſervedly ſcoff'd at by <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">In <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in that <hi>mock-Deification,</hi> which he wrote for him, in theſe words,—<hi>&amp; ipſum</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Nova Romanae</l>
                  <l>Jura ſecuris</l>
                  <l>Tremere <hi>Ocëanum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> But what ſhall we ſay to <hi>Jul. Firmicus,</hi> a Chriſtian Writer, (ſhame on ſuch flattery,) who would ſeeme to perſwade <hi>Constans</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Conſtantius</hi> his Brother, that they might expect little leſs then a Triumph, onely for their bare ventring over into the <hi>Iland: Hyeme</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> De Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re profanar. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionum, <hi>ſub fin.</hi>
               </note>, he tells them, <hi>(quod nec factum est aliquando, nec fiet,)</hi> tumentes <hi>&amp;</hi> ſaevientes <hi>undas calcâstis</hi> Ocëani Britannici, <hi>ſub remis vestris</hi> incogniti <hi>jam nobis penè</hi> maris <hi>unda contremuit, &amp; inſperatam Imperatoris faciem</hi> Britannus <hi>expavit. Quid ampliùs vultis? Virtutibus vestris victa Elementa ceſſerunt.</hi> Thus much of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Sea. And becauſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> thinks the <hi>Iriſh</hi> may as well be heer meant by <hi>Clement,</hi> you ſhall have what <hi>Solinus</hi> ſayes of that ſea too, and there alſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not unfitly expreſt.<note n="q" place="margin">Polyiſtor. ca. 35. <hi>vulg.</hi> 22. <hi>Salmaſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mare quod</hi> Iberniam <hi>&amp;</hi> Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam <hi>interluit,</hi> undoſum, <hi>&amp;</hi> inquietum, <hi>toto in anno</hi> non <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:160356:16"/>
[<note n="*" place="margin">Deeſt <hi>Salma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aestivis] pauculis diebus eſt</hi> navigabile. <hi>Clement</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>non navigabile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> unpaſſable Ocëan, <hi>and thoſe</hi> Worlds <hi>which are beyond it.</hi>] This <hi>pericope,</hi> or paſſage, is much taken notice of by the Antients; <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Origen, Hierom,</hi> and <hi>Photius,</hi> who reckons it among thoſe things in this Epiſtle which might be quarrell'd at:<note n="r" place="margin">Phot. Patriar. <abbr>CP.</abbr> Biblioth. num. 126.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. One would find fault with him, ſaies he, for making a ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of worlds to have their being without the <hi>Ocëan.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Comm. in 2. cap. ad Epheſ.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> doth but play with it, and makes uſe of it onely to ſhew his wit in deſcanting upon this Text, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Ye walked according to the courſe of</hi> this world. But <hi>Origen</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 2.</note> is more learned. He forſooth interpreting 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. where there is mention of <hi>new Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>new Earth,</hi> takes them to be thoſe Heavens, and that Earth, which our <hi>Antipodes,</hi> (he calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) generally they of the other <hi>Hemi-ſphear,</hi> do inhabit; and to back this his conceit, (every one knows his wild fancies,) he cites this place of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> I am not ignorant that the opinion, that there were <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes,</hi> got footing and credit among the learned <hi>Romans</hi> both before<note n="u" place="margin">Cic. Acad. qu. l. 4. Virgil. G. lib. 1.</note>, (yet <hi>Lucretius</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">De Nat. Rer. lib. 1.</note> explodes it,) and in the<note n="y" place="margin">Mela de ſitu Orb. lib. 1. cap. 1. Senec. epiſt. 122. Plin. l. 2. cap. 65.</note> age of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> But whether the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> then living had given it any entertainment, is a great doubt; nay it may well be denied, if we conſider with what earneſtneſs in after Ages it was oppoſed by<note n="z" place="margin">Divin. Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">De C. D. lib. 16. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and others. And ſhall we think that what <hi>Clement</hi> had once maintained this way, ſhould be by one of his ſucceſſours, namely <hi>P P. Zachary,</hi> about the year 745. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for an <hi>Hereſie,</hi> in <hi>Vigilius,</hi> upon the accuſation of <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> (if my Author deceive me not,) our otherwiſe learned Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman, the Apoſtle of the <hi>Germans,</hi> and firſt Biſhop of <hi>Mentz.</hi> It ſeems not then very probable, that by theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(mundi)</hi> he intends; or aims at the <hi>Antipodes.</hi> Doth he then by this word at random mean any parts whatever of the then habitable world, (perhaps of difficult acceſſe,) as <hi>Propertius</hi> doth in this verſe:<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <abbr>IV.</abbr> eleg. 3.</note>
               <q>Cogor &amp; è tabulâ pictos ediſcere <hi>mundos?</hi>
               </q> It doth not appear ſo neither, by reaſon they were <hi>Trans Oceanum:</hi> And I dare ſay when he wrote this Epiſtle, he had no thought <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of any new diſcoveries, though <hi>Seneca</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:160356:16"/> his contemporany would make us beleeve by his<note n="d" place="margin">Medea. Act. 2. ſc. <hi>Audax.</hi> fin.</note> 
               <hi>Venient annis ſecula ſeris,</hi> &amp;c. that he foreſaw what poſterity ſhould detect of the yet unknown world in future ages. What ſhall we ſay then? <hi>Si praecedens noſtra conjectura vera eſt,</hi> ſaith the Editioner, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanniae <hi>intelligendae veniunt.</hi> If we were right before, that <hi>Oceanus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the <hi>Britiſh Ocean;</hi> (for <hi>Libanius</hi> where he deſcribes it, as you heard before, gives the very ſame <hi>Epithet</hi> to it,) then by undeniable conſequence the <hi>Ilands</hi> antiently called <hi>Britanniae,</hi> (this that we live upon, being one, and by far the greateſt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd from the reſt by the name of <hi>Albion</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Plin. Hiſt. lib. 4. cap. 16.</note>,) muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. <hi>The</hi> Worlds <hi>beyond it.</hi> Neither let any man wonder at the inſolency of the expreſſion, when he ſhall <hi>(vice verſâ)</hi> read in holy Writ, all <hi>Europe,</hi> a third part of what was then diſcovered of the World, and whatever was on this ſide the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> call'd<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. <abbr>X.</abbr> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Inſulae Gentium,</hi> i. <hi>The Iles of the Gentiles.</hi> For we may as well almoſt call our Ilands <hi>Worlds,</hi> as a third part of the World, (of ſo great a continent,) is called <hi>Ilands.</hi> But to confirme this more then probable conjecture, I will firſt bring a place out of the Tragedy of <hi>Octavia,</hi> written by one of her own <hi>domeſtics,</hi> and while <hi>Clement</hi> was yet alive, and flouriſhing. The Author makes her ſpeak theſe words of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Claudius</hi> th' Emperor<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 1. Sc. 1.</note>:
<q>
                  <l>Modò cui totus paruit <hi>Orbis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ultra Ocëanum;</hi> cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>Britanni</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Terga dedere;</l>
                  <l>Ducibus noſtris ante <hi>ignoti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Juriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſui.</l>
               </q> What I pray you is <hi>Orbis ultra Ocëanum</hi> (by which you ſee ſhe meanes <hi>Britain,</hi>) but <hi>Clement</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>The World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea?</hi> The number need not trouble any one; that may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be anſwered for. And the languiſhing ſtile of this Tragedy, or whatever elſe it ſtands accuſed of<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>By</hi> Lipſius, <hi>and</hi> Jan. Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Var. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>, takes nothing either from its antiquity, or authority. Beſides I could tell you, a better Scholler then any that except againſt it, gives very good words of it:<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ. Scalig.</hi> epiſt. 247. &amp; 414.</note> 
               <hi>nec inepta eſt, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> futilis auctoris. Optimum poëma est.</hi> And he craves pardon for that he cannot herein, without doing wrong to his own, yeeld to any others contrary judgement whoſoever he be. Another place for confirmation heerof ſhall
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:160356:17"/> be out of <hi>Manilius:</hi> (he liv'd under <hi>Augustus,</hi> ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Clement:)</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Aſtronomic. lib. I.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>Tunc<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in deſertis habitabat montibus aurum;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ignotúſque novos pontus</hi> ſubduxerat <hi>Orbes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Joſ. Scaliger,</hi> out of the written book<note n="l" place="margin">Ex Biblioth. Monaſt. Gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blacenſ.</note> which he uſed, reads it <hi>Immotuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> n. p.</hi> adding, <hi>Non fruſtrà dixit</hi> novos orbes <hi>propter</hi> Britanniam <hi>paulò ante ſua tempora à</hi> C. Julio Caeſare <hi>detectam, quam</hi> Novum Orbem <hi>vocabant.</hi> But <hi>ignotus</hi> would have ſtood well enough. <hi>Firmicus</hi> before cals it <hi>Mare incognitum;</hi> and in the Tragedy but now cited the <hi>Britains</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>antè ignoti,</hi> and their Seas<note n="m" place="margin">Act. 1. ſc. <hi>Fulgore.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ignota freta. Scaliger</hi> indeed was one, who (ſpight of the obloquy of the Jeſuite <hi>Scheinerus</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Chriſtoph. Schein. in <hi>Roſâ urſinâ,</hi> ſeu <hi>de Macul. Solis,</hi> lib. 4. part. 2. cap. 29. p. 761.</note>, and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, the ſometime <hi>fatui nova numina ſêcli,</hi>) deſerved admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly well of <hi>Manilius:</hi> Yet where he had it, that <hi>Britain</hi> was uſually call'd <hi>Novus Orbis,</hi> I am at this time to ſeek. In my poor <hi>Adverſaria</hi> I find no ſuch thing; but that it was called <hi>Alter Orbis,</hi> many teſtimonies. The curious Reader will not think it a trouble to take a view of ſome of them. <hi>Servius,</hi> the antient and learned'ſt Grammarian, upon that of <hi>Virgil</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Eclog. 1.</note>
               <q>Et penitùs toto diviſos orbe <hi>Britannos:</hi>
               </q> Britannia, ſaith he, <hi>eſt Inſula ſita in</hi> Ocëano <hi>Septentrionali, &amp; à Poëtis</hi> Alter Orbis Terrarum <hi>dicitur.</hi> What Poëts? You had this vers erewhile upon <hi>Claudius</hi> conqueſt of it, and annexing it to the Empire:
<q>Conjunctum eſt quod adhuc <hi>Orbis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Orbis,</hi> erat.</q> But <hi>Claudian,</hi> that excellent courtly and neat Poët, ſome deal more plainly, and to our purpoſe;<note n="p" place="margin">In Stilicon. Pan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. <abbr>III.</abbr>
               </note>
               <q>
                  <l>Nec ſtetit <hi>Ocëano,</hi> remiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ingreſſa profundum,</l>
                  <l>Vincendos <hi>alio</hi> quaeſivit <hi>in Orbe Britannos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> And that <hi>Britain</hi> was <hi>Mundus alter</hi> he intimates in this:<note n="q" place="margin">Paneg. 8. in Conſ. Manlii Theodori.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>—Germanáque Tethys</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paruit, &amp;</hi> noſtro <hi>diducta</hi> Britannia mundo.</l>
               </q> But better writers then Poëts ſay as much; and therefore, that <hi>Britain</hi> was termed <hi>another World,</hi> proceeded from no <hi>lenocinium</hi> of their Art; for it was verily thought to be ſo. And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit was it that made the <hi>Roman</hi> ſouldiers ſo unwilling to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>A. Plautius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Dio, lib. 39.</note> in his expedition hither, taking it to be ſome ſervice out of the World: ſo did they imagine concerning
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:160356:17"/> 
               <hi>Britain.</hi> There is a paſſage in K. <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s ſpeech in<note n="r" place="margin">De bello Jud. lib. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lat. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Joſephus</hi> abſolutely for our turn, and which much illuſtrates this place of <hi>Clements.</hi> He tels the Jewes there, that the Romans [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] <hi>ſought for</hi> Another World [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] beyond the Ocëan, <hi>and carried their armes as far as the</hi> Britains, <hi>who before that time were unknown,</hi> or, <hi>had hardly been made mention of in Hiſtory.</hi> The Author of the <hi>Panegyrique</hi> to <hi>Constantius Chlorus</hi> th' Emperour, who died at<note n="*" place="margin">Eutrop. lib. 10.</note> 
               <hi>York,</hi> (it is falſly inſcrib'd in the ordinary books to <hi>Maximian)</hi> doth thus accoſt him: <hi>Gloriare Tu verò,</hi> Caeſar <hi>invicte,</hi> Alium <hi>Te</hi> Orbem Terrarum <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſſe; &amp;</hi> Romanae <hi>potentiae gloriam restituendo navalem addidisti Imperio terris omnibus majus elementum.</hi> And a little before he had ſaid: Britanniam Caeſar, <hi>ille auctor veſtri nominis, quum</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manorum <hi>primus intrâſſet,</hi> Alium <hi>ſe</hi> Orbem Terrarum ſcripſit <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſſe: tantae magnitudinis arbitratus, ut non circumfuſa</hi> Ocëano, <hi>ſed complexa ipſum</hi> Ocëanum <hi>videretur.</hi> I do not you ſee preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heerupon (which yet ſome have done with little thanks for their pains) make queſtion whether <hi>Caeſar</hi> was the <hi>Writer</hi> of thoſe immortall <hi>Commentaries,</hi> which we have under his name, becauſe no ſuch paſſage appears there extant:<note place="margin">Vide Clariſſ. Voſſium de <hi>Historicis Latinis.</hi>
               </note> much leſſe doe I fear there hath been heer any <hi>ſpongia deletilis</hi> from the hand of <hi>Julius Celſus,</hi> whom, by reaſon of his <hi>Recenſui</hi> in the MS. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, (no ſufficient <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to paſs ſuch a judgement by) other Philologers without calling for the ſuffrages of the <hi>Criticall Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> have reſolved to be if not the <hi>Author,</hi> yet at leaſt the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polator</hi> of thoſe excellent writings. I could far better, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Caeſars</hi> manner of relating in thoſe books, imagine that the <hi>Panegyrist</hi> took his <hi>ſcripſit</hi> rather out of ſome other piece, as perhaps his <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> which were in many books, his <hi>Orations,</hi> or <hi>Anti-Catones,</hi> or eſpecially out of his <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> which were extant, as appears by <hi>Servius</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">In li. 11. Aen.</note>, after this <hi>Panegyrist</hi>'s age, but are now with the reſt, to the irreparable damage of humane litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this reſpect, periſht by the ſame fate, which many other good writers have ſuſtained, through the malice, ſhall I ſay, or lazineſs rather, of bad men, and times? But though there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear no ſuch expreſſion any where at this day in <hi>Caeſars</hi> own words, yet I can help you with as much as that comes to, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:160356:18"/> the ſame Action and exploit of <hi>Caeſars,</hi> in a moſt polite Hiſtorian of the next Age, who compos'd an elegant <hi>Breviary</hi> of the <hi>Roman affairs</hi> under <hi>Hadrian</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Vid. Cl. Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſ. in <hi>Sparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> p. 44. ubi <hi>Flori</hi> editio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem promittit.</note>, at whoſe expedition into <hi>Britain</hi> he hath a fling, and is as well anſwered by the Emperor in <hi>Spartianus.</hi> It is <hi>L. Florus</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">De Geſt. Rom. li. 3. c. 10.</note>. Caeſar, ſaith he, <hi>omnibus terrâ mari<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> captis, reſpexit</hi> Ocëanum, <hi>&amp; quaſi hic</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pomp. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin. legit <hi>Orbis Romanus,</hi> &amp; <hi>alium.</hi>
               </note> Romanis Orbis <hi>non ſufficeret,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pomp. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin. legit, <hi>Orbis Romanus,</hi> &amp; <hi>alium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>alterum cogitavit. Claſſe igitur comparatâ,</hi> Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam <hi>petit.</hi> When firſt I met with this place cited under the name of <hi>L. Annaeus,</hi> by <hi>Pompon. Sabinus</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">In Virgil. Ecl. 1. <hi>Et peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus toto,</hi> &amp;c.</note>, Profeſſor at <hi>Rome</hi> in our Great-Grandfathers memory, I ſuppoſed it might have been out of <hi>Seneca;</hi> but upon recall of my memory, and more diligent enquiry, you have the right Author, who was alſo of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean</hi> Family, and called <hi>L. Annaeus Florus,</hi> though <hi>Stadius</hi> that writes a prolix Commentary upon him, obſerves it not, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. And yet <hi>Lactantius</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Divin. Inſtit. lib. 7. cap. 15.</note> may ſeem to have miſtaken <hi>Seneca</hi> for <hi>Florus,</hi> reckoning up the ſeverall Ages of the State of <hi>Rome,</hi> if at leaſt <hi>Florus</hi> had not that obſervation from him, which<note n="z" place="margin">Not. in Frag. Senecae.</note> 
               <hi>Lipſius</hi> rather thinks to be true. And I ſuppoſe alſo he had this expreſſion here from <hi>Velleius Paterculus,</hi> in whom concerning <hi>Caeſar</hi> you read,<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtor. li. 2.</note> alterum <hi>paenè Imperio noſtro, ac ſuo, quaerens</hi> Orbem.</p>
            <p>What need I now after theſe witneſſes to allege the forenamed <hi>Hegeſippus</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">De Excid. Hieroſol. lib.</note> the <hi>expilator</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">v. Scal. Elench. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haer. c. 4.</note> of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> in whom we read: <hi>Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> Alter Orbis, <hi>remota à confinio Terrarum?</hi> Or <hi>Solinus,</hi> whoſe words are:<note n="b" place="margin">Polyhiſt. c. 35. Salm. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Finis erat Orbis ora</hi> Gallici <hi>littoris, niſi</hi> Britannia <hi>inſula</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>non qualibet magnitudine, nomen penè</hi> Orbis alterius <hi>mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur.</hi> But for all this could you think this ſtile and language concerning <hi>Britain</hi> ſhould be retained ſo many Ages after <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (neer about <abbr>XI.</abbr>) and that by one of his Succeſſors in the Sea of <hi>Rome; Anſelmus,</hi> ſaith the Author<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gervaſ. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robern.</hi> Imagin. contra Rob. Abb. S. Aug. <hi>MS. in Cottoniana.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>ab</hi> Urbano PP. <hi>Pallium ſuſcepit, &amp; tantum ejus gratiae habuit, ut eum</hi> Alterius Orbis <hi>Papam vocaret.</hi> It is well it was ſo long ago that this ſpeciall <hi>Grace</hi> was granted to the Arch-biſhops of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> In theſe our dayes we need not now ſtand afrighted at the dire influence, of what ſome fear'd might happen from thence, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we will <hi>cum Larvis luctari,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. —</p>
            <p>Now that which gave Britain the credit to be thought ſo, was
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:160356:18"/> not onely the <hi>Ocëan</hi>'s ſeparating it from the other parts of the World, but the greatneſs alſo, and large extent thereof: For ſome Writers, ſaith <hi>Dio</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Hiſt. Rom. lib. 39.</note>, (before the Romane fleet under <hi>Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cola</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Tacit. in vitâ, &amp; Dio, ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prà.</note> doubled the Cape of<note n="g" place="margin">Ptolem. Geogr. lib. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Virvedrum,</hi> or <hi>Dunes-bay,</hi> that <hi>enorme ſpatium procurrentium terrarum</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Tacit. in vitâ, &amp; Dio, ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prà.</note>; in <hi>Tacitus</hi> Language) brought it into controverſie whether it might not rather be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Continent,</hi> as reſembling that more, in the expreſſion of <hi>Stephanus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Steph. By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zant. in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] then an <hi>Iland.</hi> That indeed in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> is ſpoken very high: <hi>Penè non minor quàm noſter Orbis:</hi> Yet may it be excuſed by the generall miſtake of thoſe times; for when he wrote, it was not certainly diſcovered to be an Iland, and therefore they might ſay what they would of it.<note n="a" place="margin">L. De Reb. Geticis.</note> 
               <hi>Cujus magnitudinem olim nemo, ut refert</hi> Livius, <hi>circumvectus eſt, multis tamen data est varia opinio, de ea loquendi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jernandos. Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cola,</hi> as is ſaid, under <hi>Domitian,</hi> was the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> that by try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all found it to be ſo. However, either the reputed greatneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or the known vaſt circuit of it, after it was diſcovered, made it generally to be called THE GREAT ILAND. You have in <hi>Ariſtides</hi> Orations, ſpeaking of it,<note n="b" place="margin">In Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiacâ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and<note n="c" place="margin">Panegyr. in <hi>Romam.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in <hi>Catullus</hi> is,<note n="d" place="margin">Epigr. 26. ubi Scalige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum adiſis.</note> — <hi>ultima</hi> Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis <hi>Inſula.</hi> And <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> the moſt flouriſhing Philologer of theſe times, and generally a very learned man, for <hi>qui ad</hi> Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Inſulam <hi>Proconſulem mittat,</hi> in <hi>Vopiſcus,</hi> doth read,<note n="e" place="margin">Caſaub. &amp; Salm. in Fl. Vopiſci <hi>Floria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Magnam Inſulam;</hi> though <hi>Caſaubon</hi> rather <hi>Britanniam Inſ.</hi> There indeed <hi>Britain</hi> is undoubtedly meant. For <hi>Procopius</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">De b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llo Vandal. lib. 1.</note> termes it, (and every body knowes it,) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. by far the greateſt of all Ilands without <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Dionyſius</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dionyſ. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andr. in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the Ilands of <hi>Britain,</hi> the <hi>greatneſs</hi> is extraordinary, or very famous, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtath.</hi> interprets it, which he doth not reſtrain neither, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine, in compariſon of any other whatſoever, within the ſame bounds that <hi>Procopius</hi> doth; which may be perchance, becauſe he was more antient. Read him as <hi>Priſcian,</hi> or elſe <hi>Rhemnius Palae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> have rendred him.</p>
            <p>But the Reader will ſay, More then enough of this ſubject; it becomes tedious, and troubleſome. Yet nothing ought to be thought ſo by us, which may any way tend to the honour and glory of this our Iland, the <hi>Empreſs</hi> of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> the <hi>Admired,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:160356:19"/> and chiefly to be eſteemed <hi>Fortunata</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">—Qua meta <hi>Britannis,</hi> Littera ſunt aliis. —Non altera ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Arva <hi>Beatorum</hi> potiùs dignata fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe Nomine, jam lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go quanquam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus iflud ab avo Intervertit <hi>Iber,</hi> &amp; ſeris addidit undis. <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> Inaugur. <hi>JA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COB. R.</hi>
               </note>, whoſe Command is only limited with the ſhoares of the Continent, being, (to ſpeak of Her, after ſo many forreign antient Teſtimonies, in the words of one of Her own<note n="*" place="margin">Sam. Daniel.</note> Poëts,)
<q>A <hi>WORLD</hi> within Her ſelf with wonders blest.</q> I will refer therefore a more exact diſcourſe heerof to another time, and a more fitting place; and the Reader likewiſe, if he think not well of this Interpretation of <hi>Clement</hi>'s words, to <hi>Plutarch</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">L. De facie in Orbe Lunae.</note>, where he diſcourſes upon <hi>Homer</hi>'s<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; δ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and to <hi>Kepler,</hi> that <hi>Atlas</hi> of the Aſtronomicall Heavens, in his learned <hi>Notes</hi> upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>A Bird called a</hi> Phoenix.] S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> being to prove and make good the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> inſtanceth in <hi>grain</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.36.</note>, which being <hi>ſown,</hi> firſt <hi>dieth,</hi> and afterwards is <hi>quickned.</hi> But his Scholler <hi>Clement,</hi> further to clear and illuſtrate the ſame doctrine unto them, maketh uſe heer of the then late renewed, and much admired Story of the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> with the diſcourſe thereupon, certainly beleeved by the many. The flight thereof into <hi>Egypt</hi> is reported by <hi>Tacitus</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Annali <abbr>VI.</abbr> A. à conditu LI. <abbr>DCCXXCVII.</abbr> Paullo Fab. L. Vitellio. Coſs. A. Chriſti. 34.</note>, and others, (yet with ſome difference,) to happen under <hi>Tiberius;</hi> about the time I preſume, or not long before, <hi>Clement</hi> was born; And <hi>Solinus</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Polyhiſt. cap. 46.</note> tels us, that, being taken ſome thirteen years after, it was by the command of <hi>Claudius</hi> ſhewn in publique at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the whole matter regiſtred for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth among the <hi>publique Acts</hi> of the City. Could I ſee thoſe <hi>Acta</hi> he ſpeaks of; or could he tell us that himſelf ſaw it, or <hi>Pliny</hi> rather, (who well might, had it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en at <hi>Rome;</hi> and whom he doth for the moſt part but tranſcribe,) I would ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Till then onely this; The p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eple of <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſe he himſelf, had a more coming beliefe, and eaſlier to be work'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then I have; except I were better ſatisfied in reſpect of ſome doubts; one of which ariſes from a paſſage in <hi>Pliny</hi> himſelf, where he tels us, that<note n="o" place="margin">Hiſt. l. 8. c. 21. <hi>Adeò naturae ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil placuit eſſe ſine pari.</hi> v. Tho. Brouni r. Cl. Pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. Epidem. lib. 3. ca. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Nature would have nothing to have a being without a Fere.</hi> However I could eaſily give way to be perſwaded, that <hi>Clement</hi> had a conceit of the truth of this pretended won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The ſimplicity indeed of the primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſuffred their belief with eaſe to be abuſed, and themſelves, as may be ſhewn by almoſt infinite inſtances, to be deluded with any thing that ſavored of <hi>Miracles,</hi> the memory of thoſe yet remaining
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:160356:19"/> freſh, which were really performed, and truly ſuch. And they thought well of this their credulity, as uſhering in an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of a divine and unlimited power in the handy-works of God. If he beleeved it not, then reckon it, if you will, among thoſe <hi>piae fraudes</hi> they talk of; and conceive that he knew well enough, how much new fangles, and <hi>teratologies,</hi> could work upon the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as well as upon their fellow <hi>Grecians</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Praebuit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriem doctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis <hi>Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> multa ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eo miraculo diſſerendi. <hi>Tac. ib.</hi>
               </note>, for Chriſtianity had not as yet wholly <hi>caſt out their old leaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet the Fathers in the following Ages, <hi>longo agmine,</hi> have either borrowed it out of <hi>Clement</hi> himſelf, or elſe received it from hand to hand, without the leaſt queſtioning of it. This we may ſee by <hi>Tertullian, Origen. Lactantius. Euſebius, Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem, Ambros, Nazianzen, Jerom, Epiphanius, Syneſius,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Vide <hi>Joan. Gazaei</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a pud <hi>Jan. Rurgers. Var.</hi> l. 2. c. 7. p. 114. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c.</note> and others; who all have followed him, or certainly the more antient of them. So that<note n="r" place="margin">Anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Tertull. lib. de Reſurrect. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Pamelius,</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Prooem. in Diatax.</note> 
               <hi>Bovius,</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Prooem. in Diatax.</note> 
               <hi>Turrian</hi> the Jeſuite are very much miſtaken in affirming ſo peremptorily that<note n="t" place="margin">Catecheſ. 18. <hi>Vide</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machan. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. de Clem. &amp; Ignat. ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptis, cap. 10. pag. 66.</note> 
               <hi>Cyril</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> took this inſtance from the Apoſtolical Conſtitutions; as will appear by comparing them two with <hi>Clement;</hi> out of whom <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſome of his other arguments and evidences for the Reſurrection. Nay, the very Author himſelf of thoſe <hi>Diatax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> (for <hi>Clement</hi>'s they are not,) is beholding to him for it: Onely he hath enlarged the narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by ſome circumſtances, which he hath added, made it come neerer a fable then it was before, and ſo the leſſe to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved. Now the Fathers indeed, having to deal with infidels and heathen-men, who granted the ſtory of the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> induced from thence a perſwaſion of the Reſurrection; that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing as it were a principle and poſition, received among themſelves. For to ſay truth, the Reſurrection was a ſtrange and uncouth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe among them, and no way reconcileable with their reaſon, and intellectuals. And therefore S. <hi>Paul,</hi> having preached, and, no doubt, ſufficiently declared the doctrine thereof at <hi>Athens,</hi> yet thoſe Philoſophicall peeple, the<note n="u" place="margin">Act. 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>Epicureans</hi> and <hi>Stoïcs,</hi> and the reſt of that learned rabble there took<note n="*" place="margin">Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be ſuch a piece of <hi>curvum Graecum,</hi> that they were preſently almoſt about to enſhrine it, and reare an Altar unto it, with an Inſcription, among thoſe forreign <hi>Numina,</hi> which they knew not what to make of them. Neither ought it to be any wonder, if they had
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:160356:20"/> very little ſentiment of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> or indeed none at all, unto whom the Great God of Heaven and Earth, he<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>who raiſed up Jeſus from the dead, the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>first fruits of them that ſleep,</hi> was no better then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The unknown God,</hi> as appeares by that <hi>Epigraphe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 17.23. Adiſis Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores in hunc locum. I ſid. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuper. Peluſ. epiſt. 69. lib. 4. &amp; vitam S. Martialis Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movicenſ.</note>, which <hi>Paul</hi> took notice of in the ſame City: and who by the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves, having the eyes of their minde veyled with the ſame thick miſt of ignorance and unbelief, was termed but<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pompeius apud Lucanum:</hi> Cappodoces mea ſigna ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſacris <hi>Incerti</hi> Judaea <hi>Dei,</hi> molliſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phone. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Incertus Deus,</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Trebell. Pollio in <hi>M. Val. Claud. Imp.</hi> ubi de <hi>MOSE</hi> ei ſermo.</note> 
               <hi>Numen incertum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet for all this I may very well obſerve in this place, that there were even among the Heathen themſelves, ſome of better Souls, who, by the meer light of Nature, (for I doe not beleeve that God did reveal unto them the <hi>riches of his bounty</hi> herein any otherwiſe then in an ordinary way,) had a ſhrewd geſſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome good ken, though at a diſtance, of the Reſurrection. Not to urge that verſe of <hi>Phocylides,</hi>
               <q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">And ſtrait we hope to come out of the earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ht. <hi>But he is thought a</hi> Christian <hi>by ſome.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q> Nor thoſe of <hi>Virgil;</hi> (for you'l ſay they were both Poëts:)
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Aeneïd. lib. 6.</note>O Pater, anne aliquas ad coelum hinc ire putandum eſt</l>
                  <l>Sublimes animas? <hi>iterumque ad tarda reverti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Corpora?</hi> Quae lucis miſeris tam dira cupido?</l>
               </q> And a little after:
<q>
                  <hi>Rurſus &amp; incipiant</hi> in corpora velle reverti:</q> I will name two others of better credit: Firſt <hi>Democritus,</hi> a Grecian, who though he were born <hi>Vervecum in patriâ, craſſo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſub a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Juvenal. ſat. 10.</note>; — yet through the glimmering, and foggy light thereof, he could make a ſhift both to diſcern, and promiſe to himſelf and others alſo, a time <hi>reviviſcendi,</hi> when <hi>as this life ſhould be iterated,</hi> or renewed, <hi>by death.</hi> Thus much<note n="a" place="margin">Natur. Hiſt. l. 7. c. 55. <hi>iterari vitam morte,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> of him: who indeed ſeems to have had a more redundant and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulant ſpleen then <hi>Democritus</hi> himſelf, in that he laughs at him for maintaining of that, which he cannot confute, I am ſure doth not, any otherwiſe then thoſe ſcoffing <hi>Philoſophers</hi> before mentioned in the <hi>Acts, Some mocked,</hi> &amp;c. a thing unbeſeeming the gravity of a <hi>Roman,</hi> and the wiſdome and authority of ſo great a man. The other is a <hi>Roman,</hi> the very <hi>Sireno-phenix</hi> of better Philoſophy, <hi>Marcus</hi> the Emperour, whoſe words are theſe:<note n="b" place="margin">M. Antonin. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. XII. § 6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <q>How comes it to paſſe, ſaith he, that the Gods having ordered all things in a fair and loving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:160356:20"/> to mankind, they have overſeen this one thing; that, whereas many very good men, and ſuch as have given evidence of their ſervice of God, and have become very familiar with him by their religious exerciſes and performances, after they are once dead, return no more, but are extinguiſht for ever? Now, (if indeed it be ſo,) know for a certain, that they would have ordered it otherwiſe, if it had been fitting to have been otherwiſe, &amp;c.</q> This he ſpeaks in a kind of condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the common received errour among the Heathen in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> But by this clauſe, or <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>if indeed it be ſo,</hi> that they reſtore not good men to life again; and by another that followes in the ſame diſcourſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>if it be not ſo indeed,</hi> that good men return again to life; it ſeemes to me moſt apparent, that this moſt divine man for his own part had a deep conceit, and a ſtrong apprehenſion of the Reſurrection of the body after death. Such excellent illuminations had theſe gallant ſpirited men beyond what the <hi>Stoa,</hi> or <hi>Peripatus,</hi> ever dreamt of.</p>
            <p>As for this paſſage of the <hi>Phenix,</hi> the Emblem of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, heer in <hi>Clement,</hi> we find no bodies exception againſt it, either before or after <hi>Photius</hi> the Patriarch of <abbr>CP.</abbr> he indeed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes his diſlike, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="c" place="margin">Biblioth. Num. 126.</note>] that the Author <hi>ſhould uſe this inſtance as an example of abſolute truth.</hi> But if he had, as he was a true learned <hi>Critique,</hi> ſo alſo conſidered when it is that the Antient writers of the Church do ſpeak <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is doctrinally and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and when <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as their own expreſſion is,) that is, as ſubſervient to their purpoſe, and by way of Rhetoricall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, perhaps he would have ſpared his cenſure. Yet he doth not therefore abdicate this Ep. from <hi>Clement,</hi> as ſome do, who think he would never in ſo ſerious a diſcourſe make uſe of the flying talk of his own Age, and a queſtionable report that had no eye-witneſs for the Author of it, a meer Pageant brought but the other day upon the ſtage; not remembring perhaps that the tale of the <hi>Phenix</hi> is of far longer ſtanding, mentioned by<note n="d" place="margin">In <hi>Euterpe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herodotus,</hi> and others, many ages before either <hi>Paullus Fabius</hi> and <hi>L. Vitellius</hi> were <hi>Conſuls,</hi> or <hi>Clement</hi> himſelf born; So
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:160356:21"/> that I needed not ſo much as to have named <hi>Ovid</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Metamorph. 15. <hi>Geo. Sandys</hi> Interprete.</note>, had not his deſcription ſo neerly agreed with <hi>Clement</hi>'s, or been indeed the very ſame. I will add it heer therefore to cloſe up this diſcourſe, and the rather, becauſe the whole buſineſſe being accounted <hi>Poëtry,</hi> which is but plain <hi>fiction,</hi> it will ſhew a great deal more hanſom in verſe; eſpecially being tranſlated almoſt aſwell to the envy, as admiration of the Reader. This is it:
<q>
                  <l>One onely fowle there is in all the Earth,</l>
                  <l>Call'd by th' <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> Phenix, who in th' wain</l>
                  <l>Of age repaires, and ſowes her ſelf again.</l>
                  <l>Nor feeds on grain nor hearbs, but on the gumme</l>
                  <l>Of Frankincenſe, and juycy Amomum.</l>
                  <l>Now, when her life five ages hath fulfill'd,</l>
                  <l>A nest her horned beak and talons build</l>
                  <l>Upon the crownet of a trembling Palm:</l>
                  <l>This ſtrew'd with Caſsia, Spiknard, precious Balm,</l>
                  <l>Bruiz'd Cinamon, and Myrrh; thereon ſhe bends</l>
                  <l>Her body, and her age in odors ends.</l>
                  <l>This breedings Corps a little Phenix beares,</l>
                  <l>Which is it ſelfe to live as many yeares.</l>
                  <l>Grown ſtrong, that load now able to transfer,</l>
                  <l>Her Cradle, and her Parents Sepulcher</l>
                  <l>Devoutly carries to <hi>Hyperion</hi>'s town:</l>
                  <l>And on his flamy Altar layes it down.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXIII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>For nothing is impoſſible for God to doe, except it be to lye.] Clement</hi> doth heer, no doubt, allude to two ſeverall places of Scripture, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. where it is ſaid, <hi>God cannot lye:</hi> and <hi>Ebr.</hi> 6.18. where we likewiſe read, that <hi>it was impoſſible for God to lye,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] which the learned<note n="a" place="margin">De Jure Bel. &amp; Pacis, lib. 2. cap. 13. § 3.</note> 
               <hi>Grotius</hi> rather renders <hi>fallere,</hi> then <hi>mentiri;</hi> as <hi>Beza,</hi> We, and generally all Interpreters do. But ſome of the <hi>Fathers,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Tho. Aquin. part. 1. qu. 25. art. 3. &amp; 4.</note> and the <hi>Schoolemen</hi> ſpecially, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſuch manner of expreſſions as theſe, whereby the <hi>Power</hi> of God may in ſome ſort ſeem to be reſtrained to bounds and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:160356:21"/> limits in reſpect of certain particular actions, not onely forgot the reverent awe and eſteem they ought to have had concerning the extent, and Almightineſs thereof; (for <hi>how little a portion</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Job 26.14.</note>, ſaith <hi>Job, have we heard of it? the thunder of his</hi> power <hi>who can understand?)</hi> But even the <hi>Hethen</hi> man's rule;<note n="c" place="margin">Cicero.</note> 
               <hi>Homini de pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Deorum pauca, &amp; timidè, ſunt dicenda.</hi> And but good reaſon; whenas to Kings, (but mortall Gods,) and concerning their power, (which is indeed, in reſpect had to the Divine, not ſo much as a poor <hi>punctum</hi> to the immenſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nivers,)</hi> one of the wiſeſt of nature's<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Solon,</hi> Plutar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho. <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> Heſychio Illuſtrio. <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtot.</hi> aliis.</note> Sons adviſed to ſpeak, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>or ſhort, or ſweet.</hi> For how much more is the <hi>Lawyers</hi> language to be approved of, then <hi>Jerom</hi>'s, that great <hi>Divine,</hi> yet both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the ſame thing? His words are, in one of his hot fits of his immoderate dotage upon <hi>Virginity:</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Epiſt. 22. ad Euſtoch. de cuſtod. virgin.</note> 
               <hi>Audenter loquar: Cùm omnia poſſit Deus, ſuſcitare virginem non poteſt poſt ruinam.</hi> The others far more moderate, and mannerly, though ſaying as much:<note n="f" place="margin">C. de rap. virg. l. Unic.</note> 
               <hi>Virginitas corrupta restitui non poteſt.</hi> I will not ſo much as name the Hethen <hi>Poëts,</hi> who enſlaved their Gods to the obſervance of conditions from a fatall neceſſity of the <hi>Destinies,</hi> which to alter they would have not more unlawfull for them, then impoſſible. And the Philo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ophers (the moſt I mean) were little better, if not worſe: So that <hi>Jupiter</hi> in<note n="g" place="margin">In <hi>Timone.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Lucian,</hi> hearing the blaſphemies, and the unreverent Speeches of <hi>Timon</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the divine Providence, and <hi>Power</hi> of God, made no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ground enough from thence to conclude him a <hi>Philoſopher;</hi> though truly he was no ſuch man. Yet ſome more generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of theirs that way may be excuſed, if withall we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand God's <hi>Will</hi> by his <hi>Power:</hi> as that of <hi>Plutarch;</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Alluding I think to <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho</hi>'s verſes: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is impoſſible for God to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that undone, which hath been done. Becauſe neither doth he will it ſhould be ſo. For<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 135.6. Pſal. 115.3.</note> 
               <hi>he hath done whatſoever he will both in heaven and earth.</hi> And indeed <hi>Plato</hi> tels us, that [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] God cannot will to alter himſelf. By which perhaps <hi>Attic Moſes,</hi> (for ſo Antiquity call'd him) meant nothing elſe but [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="k" place="margin">Ebr. 6.17.</note> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Language,] <hi>the immutability of the Counſell of God.</hi> For having in his <hi>Common-wealth</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">De Rep. l. <abbr>III.</abbr>
               </note> given leave not onely to <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> but unto <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> alſo upon occaſion, to tell a lye; yet will he
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:160356:22"/> by no meanes permit it unto God, as being a note or ſigne of infirmity and weakneſs; he by ſo much the more thereby aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and vindicating the divine and unlimited power of God. And heer, before we have done, let us obſerve, that <hi>Clement,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a thing <hi>not poſſible</hi> in God <hi>to lye,</hi> doth in the foregoing words aſſigne the reaſon thereof to be his own <hi>Will: God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that hath commanded others not to lye, much leſs will he himſelf lye:</hi> following therein S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who layes as one of the grounds of the ſame <hi>impoſſibility,</hi> the <hi>immutability of Gods Counſell,</hi> or <hi>Will;</hi> as appeares by the forenamed places. And ſo the <hi>Stoics</hi> alſo (the very beſt of Philoſophers) do ſet the <hi>Will</hi> of God as it were a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or bound to his <hi>power,</hi> and alwaies joyn them together. Hence are thoſe expreſſions out of their <hi>School:</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Sen. de Irâ, lib. 2. c. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Dii immortales, nec</hi> volunt <hi>abeſſe, nec</hi> poſſunt. And; <hi>Erras, ſi quis putat eos nocere</hi> velle; <hi>non</hi> poſſunt, <hi>nec accipere injuriam queunt, nec facere.</hi> And<note n="n" place="margin">Id. ep. 92.</note> again: <hi>Sua illis in legem aeterna voluntas eſt. ſtatuerunt, quae non mutarent.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Id. de Benef. l. 6. ca. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non poſſunt videri facturi aliquid, quaſi ut nolint;</hi> quia quicquid detinere non poſſunt, perſeverare voluerunt: <hi>nec unquam primi conſilii deos poenitet;</hi> and what follows in that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and high diſcourſe. Read <hi>Pliny, l.</hi> 
               <abbr>II.</abbr> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ad finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXIV.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Who ſhall ſay unto him, What haſt thou don?</hi> &amp;c. A very learned Gentleman,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> HA.</note> and my good friend, among ſome other doubts concerning the antiquity, and Author of this Epiſtle, maketh his quoting this place out of the<note n="p" place="margin">Wiſd. 12.12. and 11.21.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdome of Salomon</hi> to be one: (for thither is the Reader referr'd in the Margin of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi>'s <hi>Graeco-latin.</hi> edition, <hi>p.</hi> 37.) and thus he reaſons, if we miſtake him not:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> by the learned in Antiquities in former ages, is generally thought to have written that book; now he being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary with <hi>Clement,</hi> or not much antienter, it is not very probable that <hi>Clement</hi> ſhould make uſe of his authority; as not needing to prove ſo undeniable a Truth, to deſcend to ſo inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and late a teſtimony as his; that Book being not urged by the antient Chriſtians <hi>ad auctoritatem Eccleſiaſticorum dogmatum confirmandam,</hi> as <hi>Jerom</hi> tels us: For indeed
<q>
                  <l>Non tali auxilio, nec defenſoribus iſtis,</l>
                  <l>Cauſſa eget. —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:160356:22"/>
            <p>Therefore this Epiſtle may ſeem not to be of ſuch antiquity, as to have <hi>Clement</hi> for the Author thereof.</p>
            <p>For anſwer whereunto, not to be troubleſome in telling you, that the <hi>Jews</hi> had another Book under this Title, <hi>Secretiori linguâ compoſitum,</hi> &amp;c. (for it is nothing to our purpoſe; and we ſhould therein but rely upon the credit of<note n="q" place="margin">Jo. Picus in Comment. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Geneſin.</note> one, who doth not ſay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ever ſaw it;) We may in the firſt place queſtion it very wel, whether <hi>Philo</hi> were the Author of this we have; for there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>vola,</hi> nor <hi>veſtigium</hi> in his own works to prove it to be ſo, or indeed in any ones elſe antienter then <hi>Jerom,</hi> that I can now tell of. And we know full well how his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fail'd him in this point, to inſtance in no more then<note n="r" place="margin">So that he puts <hi>Seneca</hi> among his <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Epiſtles to <hi>Paul,</hi> and his back again to <hi>Seneca,</hi> ſo much approved of by him to be genuine. Now whereas he cites others authority for it, he ſhould have named them: but therein too he varies from himſelf; for one while he tels us the <hi>Jewes</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Prolog. in li. Sap.</note> affirm it; another while that <hi>ſome of the antient Writers.</hi> And for that piece of <hi>Criticiſm</hi> of his <hi>[Graecam eloquentiam redolet,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Praefat. in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros Salomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note>] it doth not ſo abſolutely (for I take not upon me now to examine it; or how neer the ſtile is to <hi>Philo</hi>'s,) conclude that this Book was never extant in the <hi>Ebrew,</hi> though loſt it ſeems before <hi>Jerom</hi>'s time; which might perhaps have been occaſioned by this <hi>Greec</hi> verſion thereof by ſome of the <hi>Helleniſts,</hi> or <hi>Jewes</hi> of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> it may be <hi>Philo</hi> himſelf. For <hi>Philo</hi>'s Legation to <hi>Rome</hi> was under <hi>Caius Caligula</hi> th' Emperour, and unto him, in behalf of his Country-men; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which many years he might have publiſht that Book in Gr. (if ever he did it) yea by far the greater part of an Age before this Epiſtle was written. But neither do learned men of later times incline to beleeve that it is of <hi>Philo</hi>'s writing. To name onely the moſt learned<note n="u" place="margin">Hugo Grot. <hi>de Satisfact. Chriſt.</hi> c. 1. p. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Grotius</hi> for all. He indeed acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth him, whoever it was that wrote it, <hi>Praestantiſſimum Scriptorem;</hi> and although not in the Ebrew <hi>Canon, Venerandam tamen habet antiquitatem, &amp; apud</hi> Chriſtianos SEMPER <hi>in pretio eſt habitus.</hi> To ſay freely what I think: Why may not <hi>Clement</hi> in this place allude to the 9. ver. of <hi>Eſay</hi> 
               <abbr>XLV</abbr>? as it is probable enough the Author of the <hi>Wiſdom of Salomon</hi> might. For before theſe words we ſee no<note n="*" place="margin">It is written.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor<note n="†" place="margin">The holy Word ſaith.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or yet<note n="x" place="margin">He ſaith ſomewhere.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſuch like; uſuall terms moſt an end with <hi>Clement,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:160356:23"/> when he cites, and doth not onely allude to, certain Scripture. Or why might he not have in his minde his Maſters words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <abbr>IX.</abbr> 19.20? the very<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> verbs are aſwell there uſed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> as the Author of that book, and <hi>Clement</hi> in his expreſſion hath no more out of either of them. Now we have told you before his manner of quoting Scripture. But by the ſame reaſon that <hi>Clement</hi> is ſaid to cite this out of the <hi>Wiſdome of Salomon,</hi> I may ſay alſo that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> doth as well borrow that inſtance of the <hi>Potter</hi> and <hi>clay</hi> from the ſame book; becauſe there we read:<note n="x" place="margin">Wiſd. 15.7.</note> 
               <hi>The potter of the ſame clay maketh both veſſels that ſerve for clean uſes, and likewiſe ſuch as ſerve to the contrary.</hi> And ſo might <hi>Clement</hi> be juſtified (in caſe he had this place thence) by an example beyond all exception: yet we conceive <hi>Paul</hi> rather had his eye upon the fore-quoted place of <hi>Eſay,</hi> or that of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> 
               <abbr>XVIII.</abbr> 6. Now what if <hi>Clement</hi> did cloth his ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in that Authors words? yet he cites them not for <hi>Scripture,</hi> no more then S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth an <hi>Iambick</hi> verſe<note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.33. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Evil communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c.</note> out of one of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander</hi>'s Comedies, without naming the Author of it. And I hope alſo that <hi>Clement</hi>'s elſewhere referring us to <hi>Hethen Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 69. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note>, and mentioning likewiſe the Story of <hi>Judith</hi> for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, may not prove more offenſive then the ſame <hi>Paul's</hi> alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the teſtimonies of<note n="z" place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>Aratus</hi> the <hi>Aſtronomical,</hi> or<note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Epimeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> the <hi>Epic,</hi> Poëts. Though there are I know a ſort of men even at this day in the world that ſtart at all that is not <hi>Canon,</hi> and call for the firing of all books, but<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Propheta</hi> mandabat ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis lib um haberet prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſacra <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blia,</hi> reliqui flammâ ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpti. <hi>Sleidan. Com. lib.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Bibles,</hi> and <hi>Almanacs.</hi> For all the mad men met not at <hi>Munster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXV.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Are not juſtified by our ſelves, or by our own wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c.] Thoſe <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſure, who ſhall light upon this place, will not (except they run to their uſuall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ſtarting-hole, <hi>The</hi> Heretics <hi>have corrupted it;</hi>) any longer cry <hi>Antiquity</hi> for their Doctrin of <hi>Merits,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification by wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes:</hi> as they do in all other points controverted between us, and them. <hi>Clement,</hi> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienteſt Writer of the Church, next the Apoſtles, you ſee knew no ſuch Doctrin: And <hi>Id ſanc notandum,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Crit. ſacri lib. 1. cap. 8. p. 143. ult. edit.</note> as <hi>Rivet</hi> ſaies very well.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXVI.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Let not the ſtrong deſpiſe the weak; let the weak reverence them that are ſtrong.]</hi> What <hi>Clement</hi> heer deſires in the Primitive Chriſtians of <hi>Corinth</hi> is ſaid to be the rare felicity (but that we
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:160356:23"/> cannot beleeve that courtly Hiſtorian's flatteries) of <hi>Tiberius</hi> age ſomewhile before:<note n="d" place="margin">Vell. Pater. cul. Hiſt. l. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Antecedit, non contemnit, humiliorem potens: ſuſpicit potentem hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis, non timet.</hi> Let theſe words bear a Chriſtian ſenſe, and <hi>Clement</hi> cannot be better <hi>gloſs'd</hi> upon; though I muſt confeſs the <hi>Gloſs</hi> is ſomewhat antienter then the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But at ſet times and hours.]</hi> A late<note n="e" place="margin">The uſe of daily publick prayers. <hi>printed 1641. p. 5.</hi>
               </note> Writer of our own,<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXVII.</abbr>
               </note> to maintain ſet times for <hi>Public Praiers,</hi> which they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> call <hi>Canonical Hours,</hi> allegeth this place of <hi>Clement:</hi> 
               <q>It ſeemes, ſaith he, by <hi>Clemens,</hi> that no ſmall part of that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or good order required by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> (whoſe minde he might beſt know, as one of his Diſciples,) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. doth conſiſt in the due obſerving of thoſe times and hours limited and preſcribed by authority for our praiers and devotions.</q> But I deſire his own words may be look'd upon, <hi>pag.</hi> 52. 53. Well: we have look'd upon them, and at firſt ſight perceive that the <hi>Author</hi> of that <hi>Treatiſe</hi> would have us to find, what indeed is not to be found there. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So that certainly himſelfe either read this whole paſſage with a great deal of oſcitancy and heedleſneſs; and ſo underſtood not <hi>Clement</hi>'s drift therein; or elſe, which is far a worſe ſhame, he hath dealt <hi>malâ fide,</hi> and ſtands guilty by the <hi>Cornelian Law</hi> as a <hi>falſary,</hi> in urging a teſtimony (which is as bad as forging one,) that witneſſeth no ſuch thing, as he takes upon him to prove; namely, that the antient <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had any ſet houres or times appointed for Public Praiers. In a word, this is the manner of <hi>Clement</hi>'s rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning: As under the Law God <hi>ordered that Oblations, and other duties of his Worſhip</hi> ſhould be performed at <hi>determined ſeaſons, ſet times, and houres,</hi> as alſo in the <hi>due place appointed,</hi> and by <hi>ſuch as were ordained</hi> therunto, according as God had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded; So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhould every one of them who were now under the Goſpel, give <hi>thanks unto God with a good conſcience,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>not exceeding the preſcribed rule of their miniſtry do thoſe things</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>that the Lord ordered them to do;</hi> and that with the ſame cheerfulneſs, and diligence, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> performed their Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and ſervic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, under the Law. For it is plain to any atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Reader that by [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] he meanes onely the obſervation of times and ſeaſons according
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:160356:24"/> to <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ordinances: The<note n="g" place="margin">John 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>true worſhippers of God in Spirit and Truth,</hi> being now no more confined<note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 4.10, 9.</note> 
               <hi>to obſerve dayes, and months, and times, and years,</hi> (being part of <hi>thoſe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 4.10, 9.</note> 
               <hi>weak and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly rudiments of the</hi> Law,) then we are, God be thanked, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of place, bound to go on Pilgrimage to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">John 4.20.</note> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time notwithſtanding the onely ſeat of his publique <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXVIII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>But the</hi> Lay-man <hi>is bound to the obſervation of Lay-ordinances.</hi>] CLEMENT, in the words next going before, doth ſet down the degrees of the <hi>Jewiſh Hierarchy,</hi> conſiſting of the <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>Levits;</hi> calling all the reſt <hi>Laics,</hi> or <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> as we now term them: that is, more obſcure, and leſs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. That heer he onely means and mentions the Orders of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, is moſt plain and evident: for thoſe of the <hi>Christian</hi> he names not till anon in what follows, where you ſhall hear of them. By how much the more I wonder, that a man of that great learning and gravity, ſhould with ſuch aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and confidence urge this place to confute the<note n="k" place="margin">Epiſcopacy by Divine Right, part. 2. § 11. p. 75. 76.</note> 
               <hi>weak ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions,</hi> ignorance, and <hi>Cavils</hi> of <hi>Vedelius,</hi> and others, (as he pleaſes to ſpeak) denying, that in <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s time (ſomewhat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Clement</hi>) any <hi>diſtinction in the Church, as of the Clergy and Laity, to be on foot:</hi> as he doth likewiſe underſtand the ſentence, ſave one, next afore this, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>So the</hi> Prieſts <hi>have their own place, or office, aſſigned them:</hi>] of Chriſtian <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Preſbyters.</hi> For <hi>Priest</hi> and <hi>Preſbyter</hi> are the ſame with him. And to back this Authority alleged out of <hi>Clement,</hi> (none at all in effect to his purpoſe,) he brings as bad a one, or worſe, out of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Smyrna: Let the Lay-men be ſubject to the Deacons;</hi> and ſo forth: (and ſo forſooth they ſhall have a fine time of it.) 'Tis true indeed, that, in thoſe ſix more genuine Epiſtles of his, there is<note n="l" place="margin">Ad Smyrn. &amp; Magneſianos.</note> twice mention of <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] But there are infinite interpolations, and additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which have by bad hands been intermixed there, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced in the current of time; and this mentioning of <hi>Laics</hi> is one of thoſe patches which have been ſow'd to the old garment, as appears by comparing the later <hi>Greec</hi> copies with the antient <hi>Latin Tranſlation</hi> out of the yet not corrupted Copies in <hi>Greec,</hi> or at leaſt not with that boldneſſe and liberty, as they have been ſince, to the unſpeakable wrong, as well of antiquity, as poſterity.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:160356:24"/>
            <p>And this being obſerved, will, with the Readers good leave and patience, give me occaſion to doe <hi>Ignatius</hi> a piece of right, for which indeed he is eſpecially beholding to that true Biſhop D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> whoſe learning it were an offence to praiſe or admire, his piety being ſuch, and the holineſs of his converſation. There is a paſſage in one of his Epiſtles, at which<note n="*" place="margin">Guil. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins <hi>in Probl.</hi> Jo. Milton, &amp;c.</note> very learned men have taken great offence, and very deſervedly. It is that to the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> where we find in the Greec edition: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note n="m" place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>My ſon,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>honour God and the King: But, I ſay; Honour God indeed as the Author and Lord of all: and the Biſhop, as the High-Prieſt: and after him we ought to honour the King.</hi> This they ſay, and truly, doth in plain terms <hi>contradict the Spirit of God in Salomon:</hi> From which preſumptuous gain-ſaying to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe <hi>Ignatius,</hi> we may take notice that this is but an adulterate piece, and foiſted in of late, which for very ſhame the greateſt friends of <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> forbear to urge in their behalfe, and it is utterly wanting in that antient <hi>Latin Interpreter</hi> of theſe Epiſtles, never publiſht, till within theſe two years by that moſt reverent and godly <hi>Primate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to theſe <hi>Laics.</hi> Of the two witneſſes we ſee urg'd, to prove a diſtinction between them and the <hi>Clergy,</hi> in the firſt age of the Church; one of them ſaies nothing to it; the other is ſpurious, and ſuppoſititious. That the word <hi>(Laic)</hi> might indeed be in ſome uſe in the moſt primitive times, we may grant, becauſe we find it heer; Yet then was it but as one of thoſe words, which the <hi>Grammarians</hi> call<note n="n" place="margin">Quae ſemel tantùm ab ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo auctore uſurpatae ſunt, <hi>v. Euſtath. ad</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and to this day it hath not gotten any room in our common <hi>Lexicons.</hi> Neither hear we any more of it after this, (except in <hi>Acula</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> Gr. who tranſlates the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 21.6.</note> 
               <hi>Shew-bread</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> witneſſeth,) till <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s time, and the <hi>Compiler</hi> of thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Constitutions,</hi> which they call <hi>Apostolicall:</hi> both who undoubtedly had it from hence, (but applied it otherwiſe,) as they had the buſineſſe of the <hi>Phenix</hi> likewiſe, before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and other things alſo. So in like manner was<note n="o" place="margin">Dionys. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarn. Plin. hiſt. li. 2. c. 17.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a known word to the world in the Apoſtles time; yet not ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the <hi>Primitive,</hi> that we can any where read of, as it was
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:160356:25"/> by the Church in after Ages, when ſhe called, not onely her ſelf, but the Epiſtles alſo of <hi>James, Peter, John,</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> Catholique. But the word it ſelf being no more rife at that time then it was, the thing then aſſuredly could not be in any very common uſe, or practice. Now in <hi>Clement</hi> himſelf, where it is onely to be found in that age, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies no more <hi>Christian Lay-people,</hi> then in <hi>Quintilian,</hi> (who liv'd when <hi>Clement</hi>)<note n="p" place="margin">Inſtit. li. 2. cap. 13.</note> 
               <hi>praecepta</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies the <hi>Catholic commands of the Church.</hi> For indeed how could it? that difference in perſons (as we may well <hi>conjecture,</hi> and not be laugh'd at for our weakneſs,) being not yet obſerved: And we know that names are not altogether of as antient birth as things themſelves are. I ſaid but <hi>conjecture:</hi> But <hi>Salmaſius</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Olim omnes Presbyteri erant Laici.</hi> De Preſ. &amp; Ep. ca. 5. p. 396. 398. &amp;c.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, will tell you aloud and peremptorily, that there was no diſtinction at all; that the <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> or Clergy, as we call them, and <hi>Laymen,</hi> were all one. For the Chriſtian <hi>Preſbyter</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Clariſs. Selden. Com. in Eutych. n. 9.</note> being derived from the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> they were no more ſeparated from the peeple by any prieſtly holineſs, then the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> among the Jewes were; who indeed had nothing of the Prieſt about them, ſave by accident, which might diſtinguiſh them from the <hi>Laity.</hi> * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
            <p>It appeares then, by what hath been ſaid, that, although after ages did admit of this diſtinction of <hi>Laity</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> in the Church, yet no ſuch difference is to be proved out of <hi>Clement,</hi> or <hi>Ignatius,</hi> as hath been pretended and urg'd, but indeed too pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily, not to ſay any more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXIX.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>After an exact view taken thereof.]</hi> Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Verb ſignifies to examine what blemiſhes there were, or what was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, in the ſacrifice, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> hath taught us out of <hi>Philo,</hi> the other <hi>Clement,</hi> and <hi>Chryſostome.</hi> In <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> who had it from this <hi>Clement,</hi> it was corrupted, till my L. of <hi>Armagh</hi> reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it. This I finde in <hi>Lucian</hi>'s language, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Firſt to ſearch and examine the ſacrifice whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were perfect and entire, or no. It is ill rendred therefore in the <hi>Lexicon</hi>'s, <hi>reprehenſoris animo confiderare, vel obſervare.</hi> And let me by the way mend a place in the learned Latin-Greec <hi>Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> printed by <hi>Harry Stephans. Aruſpex,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The antient β was very like μ, onely it wanted the tail, faſhioned thus μ, and that in ſome printed books, as in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:160356:25"/> 
               <hi>Callimachus</hi> by <hi>Frobenius</hi> for example, and divers others. So the miſtake was eaſie: Or if not ſo,<note n="u" place="margin">Altar.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeemed to the <hi>Calligraphi,</hi> or Tranſcribers, to have neereſt relation in their judgement to the <hi>Priest,</hi> and ſo took it for the former part of the compoſition of this word, rather then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The emendation is juſtified by <hi>Donat.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">In Ter. Phorm. Act. 4. ſc. <hi>Geta.</hi>
               </note> the Grammarian: <hi>Haruſpex ab harugâ nominatur: nam haruga dicitur hoſtia, ab harâ in quâ concluditur &amp; ſervatur.</hi> And <hi>Velius Longus</hi> almoſt in the ſame manner, but that I think the one may be mended by the other. <hi>Ariſpex ab ariugâ, quae eſſet hoſtia.</hi> Which is confirmed by <hi>Dionyſ.</hi> of <hi>Halicarnaſſus</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Antiq. Rom. lib. 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. becauſe he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, take a view of the ſacrifice, that it were not defective. <hi>Gloſſ. Haruſpex,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This was call'd by the Romans,<note n="z" place="margin">Plin. l. 8. c. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Victimarum probatio.</hi> Hence we read<note n="*" place="margin">Cic. 2. in Rull.</note> 
               <hi>hostiae probatae,</hi> and <hi>exta probata.</hi> Tertull. Apologetico:<note n="†" place="margin">Tibul. lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t mirer cum hoſtiae probentur penes vos à vitioſiſſimis ſacerdotibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To be</hi> Biſhops <hi>and</hi> Deacons.]<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXX.</abbr>
               </note> As to expreſs the <hi>gravity</hi> of thoſe Governours, which they had conſtituted over the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches, the Apoſtles called them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Elders,</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing the name from the 70. in the Old Teſtament. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to ſignifie their <hi>office, Clement</hi> heer intimates in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words, that they ſtiled them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Biſhops,</hi> taking alſo the denomination from the ſame <abbr>LXX.</abbr> 
               <hi>Interpreters, Eſai.</hi> 60.17. where we read out of the Ebrew, <hi>I will alſo make thy</hi> Officers<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Praefectos.</hi> Tremel.</note> 
               <hi>peace, and thine exactors righteouſneſſe.</hi> But the Vulgar: <hi>Ponam</hi> viſitationem <hi>tuam pacem,</hi> &amp;c. Now <hi>viſitatio</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Clement</hi> in this very Ep. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>In the</hi> viſitation <hi>of the Kingdome of Chriſt.</hi> That in <hi>Clement, Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> ſignifie the ſame Order, is moſt manifeſt to any attentive Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: and it may be gathered from this very place: to ſpare others more evident for it till anon. For if by <hi>Biſhops</hi> heer <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> did not mean <hi>Presbyters,</hi> it may be inferr'd very well, that <hi>Preſbyters</hi> were not inſtituted by the Apoſtles in their preaching up and down, and conſtituting Churches and officers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in ſeverall Cities</hi> and Countries, as he tels us: For why elſe are they omitted by him, whoſe buſineſs it is heer to ſet them down, and that as exactly, as he had done a little before the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Hierarchy? But it is more manifeſt by what followes. For <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:160356:26"/> reaſons thus: To turn out them, who have unblamably and in holineſs performed the office of their <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] is no ſmall ſin; But ye, <hi>Corinthians,</hi> have turn'd out your Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, (ſo he cals them they had turn'd out,) <hi>Ergo.</hi> For to ſay that<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc. by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right.</hi> part. 2. § 10. p. 60.</note> 
               <hi>belike they ejected their Biſhop, and Preſbyters</hi> too, were to ſay that which were not, and <hi>Clement</hi> never intended.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXI.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>That ſtrife and contention would ariſe about the name of</hi> Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.] <hi>I think the time is now,</hi> ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Collect. of Speeches. <hi>p. 76.</hi>
               </note> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Deering,</hi> urging this place. And yet he will not allow B<hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
               <hi>Hall,</hi> though <hi>Clement</hi> tels us that Biſhops were conſtituted by the Apoſtles, both in the foregoing, and following words, to prove from thence his <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy by Divine Right.</hi> Now whether by the <hi>name of Epiſcopacy</hi> in this place we mean the bare <hi>Title</hi> onely, or elſe the <hi>power</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the perſon and office of a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> as we underſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Romanum nomen;</hi> the learned Knight I think did not amiſſe in taking theſe words by way of a prophecy: For Epiſcopacy, as we take it at this day, ſome will tell you hath had ſhrewd girding at it many ages<note n="*" place="margin">Perantiqua, &amp; celeberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma quaeſtio de Ordine Hieratico. <hi>Selden.</hi>
               </note> ago, (and that not by <hi>Aërius</hi> onely,) before either <hi>Martin-mar-Prelate</hi> was born, or this preſent Parliament was ſummon'd.<note n="d" place="margin">In Epiſt. ubi ſe cum Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. confert.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf tels us that it was but <hi>vocabulum honoris, quod Eccleſiae uſus obtinuit.</hi> And in antient times, which is moſt to be wondred at, it was not the ſilly ſtate, and train, ſuch as it was, of ſome <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which was ſo much excepted againſt, and expoſed to cenſure, as their very <hi>want</hi> and <hi>poverty. Chryſostome</hi> got envy by it, when, but to eaſe his aged and impotent limbs, he rode up and down the ſtreets upon a poor <hi>Aſs,</hi> as often as his occaſions call'd him abroad in that great<note n="*" place="margin">Conſtantinople.</note> City: Himſelf will tell you what the peeple ſaid of him; <hi>Whoh!</hi> ſay they, <hi>he hath ſervants to attend him</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Homil. 1. in Titum.</note>, <hi>and rides about upon an Aſs: why is he placed above us?</hi> Now that you may underſtand his retinue was not great, no more then for his neceſſary uſes, himſelf again in<note n="f" place="margin">Homil. 9. ad Philip.</note> another place, makes going into publique aſſemblies with a multitude of followers, and to ride on <hi>Horſ-back,</hi> two pieces of State by no meanes to be tolerated in a Biſhop. And ſuch was the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Biſhops in the fourth Age, that being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Conſtantius</hi> to the Councel of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rimini,</hi> hodiè, ut Leander, &amp; alii.</note> 
               <hi>Ariminum,</hi> they had not wherewithall to carry themſelves over ſea, much leſs to keep
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:160356:26"/> them; but were fain to be maintained out of the Emperours Exchequer; Which though <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Hiſt. ſacrae, lib. 2.</note> highly commend in them, yet he that gave him the relation, did it <hi>quaſi obtrectans,</hi> to their diſgrace, and upbraiding them with their need and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency. How they were provided for at the Councell upon the Emperours coſt, I cannot tell: But it ſeems at home their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance was not much better then thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Biſhops, which was no more then three milch Cowes, and in caſe any of them became dry, the Pariſhioners ſupplyed them again; as their own relation was to <hi>Adam</hi> of <hi>Breme</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> whom they took in their way from <hi>Italy</hi> homeward. I may fit both with that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent character of thoſe poor countrey-biſhops of <hi>Italy</hi> in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus Marcellinus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. 27.</note>, an Hethen Hiſtorian: <hi>Quos tenuitas edendi potandi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> parciſſimè, vilitas etiam indumentorum, &amp; ſuperc: lia hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſpectantia, perpetuo Numini veriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ejus cultoribus ut puros commendabant &amp; verecundos.</hi> Not but that then there were ſwaggering Biſhops, and far unlike theſe; for in the ſame place he tels us, that the competition and contention about the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy between <hi>Damaſus</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſicinus</hi> was ſo violent, that the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes of 137. men ſlain in the quarrell were drawn out of one<note n="i" place="margin">Baſilicâ Sicinini.</note> Church, and <hi>Viventius</hi> the Lieutenant to the Emperour was forc't to make his retreit into the ſuburbs, till the rage of the peeple, and their ſtrife was ended. And the impartiall <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> makes the reaſon and grounds of theſe contentions to be their immoderate wealth, eaſe, and honour, after they were thus ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled; being then enricht with the gifts and preſents of great <hi>Ladies,</hi> they rode in Coaches through the ſtreets, they were choicely ſuited in their apparell, their diet dainty, in ſo much that their feaſts outwent the ordinary proviſion at Kings Tables. And that <hi>Marcellinus</hi> doth them no wrong heerin, the ſtudious Reader may ſee by the <hi>Conſtitution</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">L. 20. C. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. de <hi>Epiſc. Eccl. &amp; Clericis.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Valent. Valens,</hi> and <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> directed to the ſame <hi>Damaſus,</hi> forbidding all <hi>Eccleſiasticall</hi> perſons, or ſuch as belonged to them, to viſit widows houſes, &amp;c. to receive any thing from ſuch kind of weemen either by dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Legacy. If they did, that it ſhould be forfeited to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Damaſus</hi> was fain, though full ſore againſt his will, to give order for publiſhing of it in all the Churches of <hi>Rome.</hi> But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. enough of this.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:160356:27"/>
            <p>Now the contention about the name, or power, of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> was never ſo great, but the <hi>acceptions</hi> of the word before the Apoſtles time were as various.<note n="l" place="margin">In <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Euſtathius</hi> tels us that it was ſometimes taken for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>a ſpy,</hi> or <hi>ſcout.</hi> Elſewhere in <hi>Homer</hi> I finde it for a <hi>protector,</hi> or <hi>defender;</hi> and in this ſenſe <hi>Hector</hi> is call'd by his wife<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Epiſcopus Trojae;</hi> The defender of the <hi>Trojans,</hi> their wives, and children. It was an <hi>office,</hi> or <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy</hi> rather, among the <hi>Athenians,</hi> of which <hi>Suidas,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Aristophanes</hi> Scholiaſt, beſides<note n="p" place="margin">De Rep. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. ca. 35. v. Guid. Pancirol. de Magiſtr. Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipal. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Poſtel,</hi> or rather <hi>Poſſardus;</hi> but eſpecially ſee <hi>Meurſius</hi> in his <hi>Attic</hi> Antiquities. <hi>Cicero</hi> tels us that <hi>Pompey</hi> would have him to be,<note n="q" place="margin">Ad Attic. l. 7. Epiſt. 10.</note> 
               <hi>quem tota</hi> Campana, <hi>&amp; maritima ora habeat</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ad quem delectus, &amp; ſumma negotii referatur;</hi> by which words you ſee what power he had. And in the <hi>Pandects Arcadius</hi> calls them <hi>Epiſcopos</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">F. de muner. &amp; honor. l. fin. § <hi>item.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui praeſunt pani, &amp; caeteris venalibus rebus quae Civitatum populis ad quotidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num victum uſui ſunt;</hi> which is juſt as much as <hi>Clarks of the Market.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>The forenamed officers.]</hi> Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> The Apoſtles appointed <hi>Overſeërs</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that ſhould beleeve, as well in the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Corinth,</hi> as elſewhere. Where, by the way, take notice, that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s parts, and authority, in that buſineſſe, were no more then any ones elſe beſide: for <hi>Clement</hi> ſpeaks generally <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Our Apostles.</hi> Secondly, we may gather from <hi>Clement,</hi> that not onely the Apoſtles themſelves, but<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>others alſo taken notice of for their prudence,</hi> did conſtitute Biſhops, and Deacons; but it was with the generall conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole Church; [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] otherwiſe, they were not thought lawfully called, or choſen to their office; and ſo might not challenge any ſubjection, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, from the peeple.</p>
            <p>Now in defining what <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> theſe were, which the Apoſtles conſtituted; and in aſſigning every firſt Biſhop his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>place,</hi> or <hi>ſeat,</hi> I conceive Antiquity did not a little miſtake; not to ſay they dealt too peremptorily and preſumptuouſly therein. That I may not be thought to take too much upon me in ſo high, and ſeemingly arrogant a cenſure; I ſhall, as-well for the Readers ſatisfaction, as for mine owne excuſe and defence,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:160356:27"/> alledge a very notable place out of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> eſteemed generally the <hi>Father</hi> and fountain of <hi>Church History,</hi> who directly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth it a thing of great difficulty, to ſet down who were left by the Apoſtles the Biſhops of ſeverall Churches, confeſſing all the light he had heerin to come from the <hi>Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epistles.</hi> The place is <hi>Eccl. Hist. lib.</hi> 
               <abbr>III.</abbr> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 
               <abbr>IV.</abbr> whither the Reader may have his recourſe at pleaſure. Now for us to make our boaſts of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and to ground our diſcourſe, in the point we have in hand, upon the teſtimony and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the antients, when as <hi>Euſebius</hi> himſelf, one ſo antient, and that made ſuch diligent ſearch and enquiry into this buſineſs, freely confeſſeth, that all the certainty of his knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about was from meere Scripture, is a thing in my conceit of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme lightneſs and vanity. Not to adde heer, what I formerly took notice of, how great a flaw and breach there is in the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the firſt times of the Church next the <hi>Acts,</hi> which indeed did ſet the invention of after ages on work to write a <hi>Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in place of thoſe true <hi>Records,</hi> which moſt likely periſhed, at what time the flame of perſecution devoured the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> themſelves not more, then their particular <hi>Acta,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the future gave them moreover in command.]</hi> The Gr.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXIII.</abbr>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I tranſlated it as you ſee, having then in my mind what <hi>Plato</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignified; and being now in haſt, I let it paſſe ſo. Perhaps upon advice with ſome to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe me better, I ſhall alter it. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> had turned it; <hi>ac de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptas deinceps miniſtrorum officiorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vices reliquerunt,</hi> reading by conjecture <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Copy.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher: Eum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ordinem deinceps praeſcripſerunt.</hi> Salmaſius: <hi>Et interim etiam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum dederunt.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hall: <hi>and gave thereupon a deſigned order or liſt of Offices;</hi> coming neereſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Turner</hi> of <hi>Merton</hi> Colledge would have it read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="t" place="margin">Vide Dn. Armachan. de <hi>Ignat.</hi> ſcript. ca. 18. p. 137.</note> 
               <hi>ut continuatio Epiſcopatus ab Apoſtolis ſtabilita ſignificetur;</hi> and this reading is confirmed for him by a place in <hi>Nazianzen:</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">What the Lord hath, ordained by his Apostles, thoſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main good and firm.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaking of the Apoſtles conſtituting of Biſhops. It is in his Epiſtle to <hi>Dracontius,</hi> who had forſaken his Epiſcopall function: So that <hi>Graham,</hi> late B. of <hi>Orkney,</hi> was not the firſt that voluntarily took upon him
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:160356:28"/> 
               <hi>ſuch a Penance,</hi> as is averred. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bois</hi> of <hi>Ely</hi> had a thought it might be read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by which <hi>choice,</hi> or <hi>Election</hi> is underſtood. We ſee with what diſagreement this ſhort ſentence is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It remains therefore onely that we cry out with the Poët,— —<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>! And yet let me further obſerve for the more curious Readers ſake, that this very word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned little leſſe trouble in one of <hi>Conſtantinus Porphyrogenneta</hi> the Emperours <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> where it is read ſcarce with any good ſence: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. as <hi>Leunclavius</hi> ſet it forth, and tranſlates it, <hi>Quum reſtitutio fit in poſſeſſionem, ſi quidem in cauſſâ pauperum,</hi> &amp;c. But the learned French Lawyer <hi>Carolus Labbaeus</hi> in a later edition thereof, which I now uſe, mends it thus out of his written book: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. rendring it <hi>Poſſeſſione autem in ſolutum datâ,</hi> or, <hi>In poſſeſſione facta ſolutione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXIV.</abbr>
               </note>—<hi>their Epiſcopacy. Bleſſed are thoſe Elders.</hi> —] The Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. &amp;c. Which the Author of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy by Divine Right</hi> tranſlates: — <hi>theſe offices of Epiſcopacy. And withall, bleſſed are thoſe Presbyters.</hi> You ſee what he drives at by adding <hi>de ſuo</hi> this <hi>Nota</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>[And withall,]</hi> wanting in the Originall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXV.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>In the very beginning of his Goſpel.]</hi> He meanes <hi>Paul</hi>'s I to the <hi>Corinthians. Paul</hi> himſelf <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>according to my Goſpel,</hi> that is, my <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the doctrine which I preached, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> interprets him: Not that <hi>Paul</hi> is to be thought ever to have written the hiſtory of Chriſts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or converſation in the fleſh. <hi>Ex his,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Exercit. ſac. lib. 6. ad dict. ad <hi>Rom.</hi> I.</note> ſaith the accurate <hi>Heinſius, ſimilibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> locis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxiſſe videtur, ut antiqui</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>nomine ſcripta Apostoli cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;</hi> alleging this place of <hi>Clement:</hi> And he adds moreover, from the word going before, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the beginning,] Ex hoc ſuſpicari fortè quis poſſit, primam ordine, quae prior nunc eſt ad</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthios, <hi>tunc habitam.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> likewiſe brings a place out of<note n="x" place="margin">Contra A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollinar.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> where he citing this ſentence out of the Epiſtles of <hi>John;</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>The whole world lyeth in wickedneſs;</hi> beſtows likewiſe upon them the Title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Goſpel. Clement</hi> refers you to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Every one of you ſaith, I am of Paul, and I of Apollos, and I of Cephas.</hi> By occaſion of which words I might heer take upon me to make a defence for <hi>Jerom,</hi> whoſe words, urging
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:160356:28"/> this place of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome do force to ſuch an interpretation, as if by it he would prove, that ever ſince the time that theſe words were caſt out by the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the equality among <hi>Presbyters</hi> ceaſed, and that thereupon one was placed as a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or Overſeër, above the reſt. But this matter is<note n="z" place="margin">v. Salm. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Petar. de Epiſc. cap. 4.</note> already <hi>ab aliis occupata.</hi> And although <hi>Jerom</hi> had written ſo; (which he doth not, as will appear to any one that ſhall diligently examine his words,) yet this Epiſtle written by <hi>Clement</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> neer about <abbr>XL.</abbr> yeers after that of <hi>Paul</hi>'s unto them, evidently ſhews that the ſame <hi>Idea</hi> and form of government remained ſtill among them. Not to tell you, which I have done before, that <hi>Jerom</hi> was very well acquainted with this Epiſtle, as who took the pains to tranſlate it into <hi>Latin:</hi> and ſo the leſs likely to think or publiſh any ſuch thing, finding ſo great proof and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the contrary, as in the reading heerof he needs muſt have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For your ſiding was with Apoſtles.] Obſervabis hîc,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXVI.</abbr>
               </note> it is the learned <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his obſervation, Cepham <hi>in Epistola ad</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthios <hi>de</hi> Petro <hi>Apostolo</hi> Clementem <hi>intellexiſſe, cùm quidam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretum de quodam alio Cepha acceperint.</hi> Sure thoſe <hi>Interpreters</hi> he meanes were ſuch, as did not like to ſee <hi>Peter</hi> rankt after <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, ſo much it ſtood againſt his pretended <hi>Primacy.</hi> And yet the Antients talk of another <hi>Cephas,</hi> that ſhould be one of the Seventy <hi>Diſciples,</hi> of whom <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> in<note n="a" place="margin">Eccl. hiſt. lib. 1. ca. 123.</note> 
               <hi>Euſeb.</hi> and the counterfeit <hi>Dorotheus.</hi> But for ſatisfaction hear <hi>Jerom</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Gal. cap. 2.</note>, who tels us, <hi>Alterius neſcio cujus</hi> Cephae <hi>neſcire nos no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, niſi ejus qui &amp; in Evangelio, &amp; in aliis Pauli Epistolis, &amp; in hac quoque ipſa modò Cephas, modò Petrus inſcribitur.</hi> Now that which <hi>Clement</hi> tels the <hi>Corinthians</hi> heer, is this; That, whereas in the former <hi>ſchiſms</hi> and <hi>factions</hi> they followed and adhered to ſuch as were either <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, or elſe <hi>one</hi> that had extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary teſtimony from them, they now had for the ring-leaders of their ſedition a few perſons of far inferiour quality; and therefore their offence was the greater, and themſelves left the more inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing then there are many Gates.]</hi> This <hi>pericope,</hi> or paſſage,<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXVII.</abbr>
               </note> is tranſcribed, as you find it heer, by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. lib.</hi> 4.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:160356:29"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXVIII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Say one be faithfull,</hi> &amp;c.] So likewiſe is this cited by the ſame <hi>Clement,</hi> in the ſame book, and alſo in the <abbr>VI.</abbr> but with ſomewhat more difference in the reading.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XXXIX.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Who is able to expreſs the bond and tye of Gods love?]</hi> This ſentence we finde tranſlated in <hi>Jerom,</hi> who makes uſe of it in his <hi>Comment.</hi> on the <abbr>IV.</abbr> Chap. to the <hi>Epheſ. Cujus res,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp;</hi> Clemens <hi>ad</hi> Corinthios <hi>teſtis eſt, ſcribens;</hi> Vinculum charitatis Dei quis poterit enarrare?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XL.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>I will depart, Ile go my wayes, whitherſoever,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>Epiphanius</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 1. Haereſ. 27.</note>, writing againſt the <hi>Carpocratians</hi> hereſie, mentions theſe words of <hi>Clement</hi>'s, but with ſome difference: and beſides, he applyes them to another occaſion and purpoſe, then to what <hi>Clement</hi> uſes them heer. For telling you that <hi>Clement</hi> received impoſition of hands from <hi>Peter,</hi> yet refuſed the Biſhoprick of Rome, untill ſuch time as <hi>Linus</hi> and <hi>Cletus</hi> were dead, he adds this reaſon; for he ſaies, ſaith he, in one of his Epiſtles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. <hi>I depart, I go my wayes; onely let the people of God have reſt and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Which words <hi>Clement</hi> heer preſcribes to be us'd by the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in caſe troubles or contention did ariſe in that Church through any of their means: <q>Is any one bravely ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited among you? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let him ſay, If through my means this ſedition, or contention, or theſe ſchiſms proceed, I wil depart. &amp;c.</q> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath a paſſage, (for which, if for any, he rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerved the title of <hi>Golden-mouth</hi> beſtowed on him by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,) which while he pen'd; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> conceives he had his eye upon this of <hi>Clement:</hi> His words are; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="d" place="margin">Homil. 11. ad Epheſ.</note> &amp;c. <hi>If you conceive or ſuſpect theſe things of us, we are ready to depart, and to deliver up our power to whomſoever ye pleaſe: onely let the Church be at unity within it ſelf.</hi> A rare temper! and not to be found among the men of this Age. Now becauſe <hi>Clement,</hi> in what immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately follows, doth commend the earneſt endeavours and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings of <hi>Hethen</hi> men for the conſervation of the peace and quiet of thoſe <hi>States</hi> they liv'd in, I will parallel this place of <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> with one aſcribed to the moſt eloquent of the race of <hi>Romulus;</hi> as he was eſteemed of all the <hi>Chriſtians: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilius duxi,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Declam. in Salluſt. <hi>Cicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> tributa.</note> 
               <hi>quamvis fortunam unus experiri, quàm univerſo populo</hi> Romano <hi>civilis eſſem diſſenſionis cauſſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLI.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Many Kings and Governours.</hi> &amp;c.] He meanes ſuch as <hi>Codrus,</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:160356:29"/> and <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> among the <hi>Grecians; Genucius Cippus,</hi> and <hi>M. Curtius,</hi> among the <hi>Romans;</hi> with others, in both Hiſtories, endowed with the like brave and gallant ſpirits for the Public, not ſo generally taken notice of. Next after he bringeth in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith,</hi> who hazarded her own life to ſave the City wherein ſhe dwelt; an <hi>Apocryphall</hi> ſtory among the <hi>Jewes.</hi> That <hi>Clement</hi> thought it ſo, his placing it after mention of <hi>Hethen</hi> examples, though he inſtance in no particular, may ſerve for an argument. For there is ſcarce any <hi>Greec</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> Hiſtorian of better note, that is not to be preferr'd, in matter of truth, before it, the <hi>Macchabees,</hi> or any other hiſtoricall piece in that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or collection of writers. Now if enough hath not been already ſaid, in what goes before, for defence of <hi>Clement</hi> in this behalf,<note place="margin">Num. <abbr>XXIV.</abbr>
               </note> let the ſtudious Reader take notice, that not onely <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> cite the Apocryphall writings of <hi>Enoch,</hi> and the latter the book alſo <hi>De dimiſsione Moſis,</hi> or of his <hi>Death;</hi> (though indeed, as the admired <hi>Joſ. Sealiger</hi> hath well obſerved, thoſe <hi>Fragments</hi> we now have of <hi>Enoch</hi> are more corrupt by later additions and interpolations of the <hi>Jews,</hi> then they were formerly in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times;) But <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf likewiſe hath made uſe of divers places in his Epiſtles, taken out of other <hi>Apocrypha</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as hath been obſerved by the Fathers of the Gr. Church. In the <abbr>I.</abbr> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> out of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> of <hi>Elias;</hi> in that to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> out of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> of <hi>Moſes;</hi> in that to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> out of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> of <hi>Jeremy.</hi> Not that it follows from hence, that the Apoſtle approved of all he found written in theſe books, any more then he approved the ſeverall love-toyes, and amorous paſſages, in <hi>Menanders</hi> Comedies; an <hi>Iambic</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence out of whom notwithſtanding he borroweth, as you heard before. See the incomparable<note n="f" place="margin">Exercit. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crar. lib. 18. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Heinſius</hi> upon 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In time of a raging pestilence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLII.</abbr>
               </note> 
               <hi>upon anſwer received from the Oracle.]</hi> I do not more readily remember any example of this kind, which I could think CLEMENT might intend to, then that of <hi>Oedipus.</hi> I conceived at firſt our Author might have had this out of ſome Gr. <hi>Tragedy</hi> of him. Examining <hi>Sophocles</hi> his <hi>Oedipus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as moſt likely, I received not ſo much ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in my ſearch, as in the excellent Latin <hi>Oedipus,</hi> which
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:160356:30"/> my learned good friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Farnaby</hi> adjudges to <hi>L. An. Seneca,</hi> the very <hi>Siren</hi> of better Philoſophy, againſt the judgement of <hi>Heinſius,</hi> from whom yet in other things it is not his cuſtome to diſſent. In that Tragedy conceive the <hi>Thebans</hi> afflicted, and onely not conſumed, with a grievous peſtilence. The <hi>Oracle</hi> conſulted, returns <hi>Anſwer:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mitia</hi> Cadmeis <hi>remeabunt ſidera</hi> Thebis,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si profugus</hi> Dircen Iſmenida <hi>liqueris</hi> hoſpes, &amp;c.</l>
               </q> meaning <hi>Oedipus;</hi> who being acquainted therewith, to ſtop the current of this deſtructive evil, whereof his inceſt had been the cauſe, he ſtrait ſets forward to a voluntary exile, and is brought in beſpeaking his languiſhing <hi>Citizens</hi> with this ſad <hi>farewell,</hi> yet ſuch as did bid good cheer and health to them after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 5. ſc. <hi>Bene.</hi>
                     </note>Quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> feſſi corpore, &amp; morbo graves,</l>
                  <l>Semianima trahitis corpora; en, <hi>fugio, exeo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Relevate colla; mitior coeli ſtatus</l>
                  <l>Post terga ſequitur. quiſquis exilem jacens</l>
                  <l>Animam retentat, vividos hauſtus levis</l>
                  <l>Concipiat. Ite, ferte depoſitis opem.</l>
                  <l>Mortifera mecum vitia terris extraho.</l>
               </q> This example ſuits juſt with <hi>Clement</hi>'s purpoſe, but that you'l ſay the ſtory is meerly poëticall. Let it be ſo: yet thoſe words of <hi>Oedipus — fugio, exeo:</hi> remember me again of <hi>Clement</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i. <hi>I will depart, I'le go my wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLIII.</abbr>
               </note>
               <hi>Become ſubject to your Elders.]</hi> Beſides what hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before; <hi>Clement</hi> tels the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that for one or two factious perſons ſake, their Church had rais'd a ſedition againſt their <hi>Presbyters:</hi> He tels them in another place, that it ſhould be the onely and earneſt reſolution of every noble, mercifull, and charitable Chriſtian among them, forgetting and forſaking their own private aimes and intereſts whatſoever,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to indeavour the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> of <hi>Chriſts flock</hi> and peeple, and of the <hi>Presbyters</hi> placed over them. And in this place he adviſeth thoſe that had begun theſe troubles, and whoſe the ground-work was of this ſedition,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to repent, and by changing the pride of their tongue into the humility of heart, to become <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>obedient</hi> to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:160356:30"/> their <hi>Preſbyters.</hi> And read I ſay the whole Epiſtle over, and tell me then, whether ſolitary <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> hath any ground therein, or any practice thereof can be proved from thence; or that the Church, either of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Corinth,</hi> were governed any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, at that time when it was written, (at leaſt ſo far as may be made to appear from any plain paſſage thereof,) then by Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters: which notwithſtanding hath been pretended more then once; and among others, as our Brethren of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> can bear witneſs, by one, who was ſometime <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> among us, with a great deal more confidence, then ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Now what remaines there, but that the peeple of God, taking ſerious notice unto whom they owe obedience and ſubjection under <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in thoſe things that belong to God, ſhould with all readineſſe and cheerfulneſſe undergo and perform the ſame. And withall,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem.</note> having the <hi>Charter</hi> of their liberties and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges reſtored unto them again, as it were <hi>postliminiò,</hi> and ſo evidently aſſerted in reſpect of their particular prerogatives in the <hi>election</hi> (as it is in all reaſon and equity a thing indeed moſt fitting) of thoſe Miniſters and Officers, to whom they are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſubject; it becomes them to be very wary and prudent, and exceeding circumſpect, that they neither admit any, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves unto ſuch, who have yet remaining upon their ſouls that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſervil <hi>capillitium,</hi> as <hi>Socrates</hi> expreſſion is in <hi>Plato</hi> of ſome Magiſtrates made choice of at <hi>Athens.</hi> That they do not I ſay place ſuch in eminence above them, and as it were at the <hi>Helm,</hi> who, if a right examination were taken of their life and qualities, would ſcarce be thought fitting to have a place aſſigned them at the very <hi>ſink,</hi> or <hi>pump.</hi> They ſhould providently bethink themſelves what parts, what endowments, what converſation, what knowledge, what ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſoule, what command of affections is required to ſuch an employment, to ſo weighty an undertaking; it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</q> a <hi>buſineſs,</hi> which, if any other under Heaven, challengeth exact <hi>managing</hi> and <hi>ſteerage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:160356:31"/>
            <p>But if, through want of care and foreſight herein, they chance to prove remiſs, or, which is worſe, ſhall be ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (without queſtioning them,) any whatever they be, that ſhall affect dominion over them and their conſciences, they will therein but ſin againſt their own ſouls, in betraying and giving up that <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.23.</note> liberty of theirs, which coſt ſo dear, to the inſolency and mercileſſe tyranny of no better then meer <hi>idiots;</hi> who as they are themſelves altogether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo would they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar others of thoſe meanes, which lead to the knowledge of heavenly <hi>myſteries;</hi> and not ſo only, but like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſhut up the Kingdome of Heaven againſt men; neither going in themſelves, nor ſuffring them that are entring to go in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLIIII.</abbr>
               </note>* * * * * * *.] Concerning this <hi>lacuna,</hi> or <hi>hiatus,</hi> ſee M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Yong</hi> in the end of his <hi>Notes.</hi> I could think a ſmall parcell of that which is ſwallowed up, and loſt therein by the injury of time, might be recovered out of <hi>Baſil</hi> the <hi>Great</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">De Sp. S. ad Amph loch. cap. 29.</note>: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— <hi>But alſo the more antient</hi> Clemens <hi>ſaith;</hi> (to diſtinguiſh him from <hi>Clem.</hi> of <hi>Alexandria:</hi>) The words he cites out of him are theſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i. <hi>God liveth, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and that Holy Spirit.</hi> It is not to be thought that <hi>Baſil</hi> would cite this out of any ſuſpected writing of <hi>Clement</hi>'s; and we know that none, which now go under his name, were accounted genuine by the antients, except onely this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> we have in our hands. So likewiſe once I thought, that <hi>Clement</hi>'s urging the autority of <hi>Sibylla</hi> for <hi>the judgement of the wicked by fire</hi> in the end of the world, might have been a portion of this breach, or of what we heer ſee loſt; for which he is alleged by the Author<note n="i" place="margin">Reſp. ad Quaeſt. 74.</note> (common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi>) of the <hi>Queſtions ad Orthodoxes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in his Epiſt. to the Corinthians.</hi> But the learned D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Diſſert. de Clem. &amp; Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. ſcript. cap. 10. p. 65.</note> would have this paſſage taken out of <hi>Clem.</hi> 
               <abbr>II.</abbr> Epiſt. unto them, which antiquity generally abjudicated from him; and the rather, becauſe thoſe<note n="l" place="margin">Extant apud Lactan. l. de Ira Dei, c. 23. vide Caſaub. Exerc. contra Baron. de Sibyllinis.</note> 
               <hi>Sibyllin</hi> verſes to this purpoſe are ſince <hi>Clement</hi>'s time, and written by the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and ſo could not be made uſe of by him; though indeed Hethen men, <hi>Ovid, Seneca,</hi> and others before him beleeved the worlds finall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration. Neither is it likely that <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> being of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:160356:31"/> that ſtanding, and extraordinary learning, ſhould ſuffer his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to be abuſed with forgeries. Such impoſtures cozened and deluded after times; and in his, onely began to breed. So that I may uſe the citing of this paſſage out of <hi>Clement,</hi> as an additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall argument to thoſe many others, to prove this writing to be none of <hi>Juſtins;</hi> notwithſtanding that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Homes</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Animadver. againſt M. <hi>Tombs</hi> Inſtant-Bapt. cap. 13. p. 110. 111.</note> religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned Gentleman, troubles himſelf ſo much to aſſert and vindicate it to be his genuine work; which yet he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perſwade the learned world of men to beleeve. <hi>Hierom's</hi> Latin Tranſlation, could it be but found, would clear all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God the Beholder</hi> and Deſcryer <hi>of all things.</hi>] Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLV.</abbr>
               </note> A word onely to be found heer, and in <hi>Polycarpus</hi> his Epiſtle; who had it hence. The <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> is call'd by <hi>Nazianz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our High-Prieſt, and Ruler.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLVI.</abbr>
               </note> The learned and induſtrious Critique <hi>Photius,</hi> Patriarch of <abbr>CP.</abbr> me thinks is too <hi>Criticall</hi> in his cenſure of <hi>Clement</hi> for theſe expreſſions. The third thing that he takes exceptions againſt in this Epiſtle, is, that <hi>Clement</hi> calling our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Our High-Prieſt and Ruler,</hi> he doth not withall beſtow loftier titles upon him, and more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming his Majeſty, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Certainly his mentioning of Chriſt in ſeverall places is in very honorable terms; ſuch as theſe; Chriſt Jeſus <hi>our ſaving health;</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſt of our Oblations; The Guardian and Succourer of our weakneſs; By him we look up to the Higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By him it pleaſed the Lord to give us a taſt of immortall knowledge, who being the brightneſs of his</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which <hi>Ebr.</hi> 1. is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 3.4. whence <hi>Clement</hi> hath this, and what follows next.</note> 
               <hi>Majeſty, is by ſo far greater then the Angels,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our Lord Chriſt</hi> Jeſus <hi>the Scepter of the Majeſty of God,</hi> &amp;c. But indeed in the following ſentence <hi>Photius</hi> bites in his words again; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and yet he doth not, ſaith he, any way openly therein defame the name of Chriſt. Which I pray who could ever imagin that <hi>Clement</hi> would do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Claudius, and Ephebus, and Valerius, Biton, and Fortunatus.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <abbr>XLVII.</abbr>
               </note> By the hands of theſe five perſons the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> conveyed this <hi>Pareneticall</hi> Epiſtle, or <hi>Hortatory</hi> to peace and mutuall conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, to their Brethren of the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> I find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing recorded of them by the Antients; ſo that had it not been
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:160356:32"/> for this mention of them, they, together with their memories, might have periſhed in utter oblivion. It hath far'd better with ſeverall Saints of the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament, for whom ingenious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity hath coyned <hi>Biſhoprics,</hi> beſide other fortunes. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of them however deſerves reſpect, though but for this onely employment in Gods Church. Three of their names heer are meerly <hi>Roman.</hi> Whether one of them, <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> might be he, whom<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> mentions, and by whom, with <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanas, Achaïcus,</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> his firſt to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> is ſaid to be ſent unto them, I dare not ſay: much leſſe, that it was that <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> whom, in<note n="p" place="margin">Antiq. l. 18. cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Joſephus, Agrippa</hi> ſends to <hi>Rome</hi> to make complaint to <hi>Caligula</hi> of <hi>Herod</hi> the Tetrarch; The time in neither reſpect will well bear it. <hi>Ephebus,</hi> is a <hi>Grecian</hi> name; as is alſo <hi>Biton;</hi> For we find one <hi>Biton,</hi> a long while before <hi>Clement</hi>'s time, who was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> or the <hi>Meaſurer of his journeys</hi> in all his forreign Expeditions, whom<note n="q" place="margin">Lib. 6. cap. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> miſ-names <hi>Beton.</hi> I have<note n="r" place="margin">MS. Gr. in Biblioth. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg. Magdal. Oxon.</note> ſeen alſo ſome pieces of one <hi>Biton</hi> among the <hi>Greec</hi> writers of <hi>Mechanics,</hi> or about <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Engins,</hi> uſually joyned with<note n="ſ" place="margin">Malè <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> dictus Th. Jameſio in <hi>Eclogâ</hi> MSS.</note> 
               <hi>Athenaeus,</hi> an Author of the ſame ſubject, ſtill extant in the armaries of ſome <hi>Libraries,</hi> but as yet unpubliſh't.</p>
            <p>CLEMENT'S <abbr>II.</abbr> Ep. is yet remaining in ſome good part of it; but being <hi>rejected</hi> by the antients, as <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> out of him; and accounted <hi>ſuppoſititious,</hi> as <hi>Photius</hi> tels us, I have neglected therefore the Tranſlation of it. Thoſe other writings alſo, which go under his name at this day, are no better thought of by ſuch as are moſt able to judge of things of this kind. No body will wonder that the holy forgery of former times made ſo bold with <hi>Clement,</hi> who doth either already know, or ſhall hear of, not onely ſo many <hi>Apocryphall Goſpels</hi> under ſeverall <hi>Saints</hi> names; of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtle to the <hi>Laodiceans;</hi> of the<note n="t" place="margin">Extant lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guâ Armen. v. D. Armach. in Ignat. Ep. ad Trall. not. 84. &amp; Joan. Gregor. in Obſervat. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Corinthians</hi> Epiſtle to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and of his <abbr>III.</abbr>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Extant lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guâ Armen. v. D. Armach. in Ignat. Ep. ad Trall. not. 84. &amp; Joan. Gregor. in Obſervat. &amp;c.</note> Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in anſwer to theirs; of <hi>Seneca</hi>'s and <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles one to another; (wherewith good S. <hi>Jerom</hi> himſelf was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived;) But of <hi>Ariſtotle de Pomo, Plato de Vacca, Ovid de Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula,</hi> and others; in which writings, there is not onely hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mention of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> likewiſe.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:160356:32"/> The well meaning Chriſtians of antient times had a pretty conceit in them, that by this fine cozenage they ſhould with more eaſe win the <hi>Hethen</hi> to embrace their Religion, when they ſhould ſee the Author, and chief profeſſors of it, well ſpoken of by ſuch great names as thoſe before mentioned. But good men (as ſome errour is ſtill incident to all forgery) they uſually of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended therein againſt the true account of <hi>Times,</hi> and as fowly, as at this day the <hi>Turks</hi> do in their wild <hi>Chronology,</hi> making S.<note n="u" place="margin">Qui eſt ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <hi>Chederles.</hi> vid. Busbeq. epiſt. 1.</note> 
               <hi>George</hi> one of <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Great</hi>'s Commanders, and <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf <hi>Salomon</hi>'s Generall; as they do likewiſe (which to hear, and bear with it, we had need to have aſwell pity, as patience,) make <hi>Job</hi> the <hi>Controuler</hi> of his HOUSE.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Annotations.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>To be amended, or altered.</head>
            <p>PAge 21. lin. 7. for, <hi>in them,</hi> read, <hi>they.</hi> p. 26. l. 14. for, <hi>of his beauty.</hi> r. <hi>of the beauty thereof.</hi> p. 44. l. penult. lege <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 45. l. 5. f. <hi>that were.</hi> r. <hi>that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called were.</hi> p. 49. l. 7. f. <hi>in,</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> p. 50. l. 19. lege <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 51. l. 27. r. † <hi>Clement,</hi> taking the mark from before the word <hi>(Epistle)</hi> in the next line. l. 28. for, <hi>then with him,</hi> r. <hi>himſelf then being.</hi> p. 55. l. 32. f. <abbr>CC.</abbr> r. <abbr>M.</abbr> and <abbr>CC.</abbr> p. 58. l. 20. f. <hi>ſeemes to have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m out of the.</hi> r. <hi>ſeems to have had in his minde the.</hi> p. 67. l. 14. r. <hi>Jornandes.</hi> p. 72. l. 19. r. <hi>breeding.</hi> p. 73. l. 29. lege <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ibid. for <hi>Attic.</hi> r. <hi>this Attic.</hi> p. 80. l. 31. lege <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 81. l. 10. after <hi>hoſtia,</hi> adde, <hi>And not from</hi> Ara, <hi>as ſome would have it.</hi> p. 84. l. 11. r. <hi>Campania.</hi> There may chance to be ſome other miſtakes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Tranſcribers pen, or the Workes themſelves.</p>
            <p>In the Margin.</p>
            <p>Preface, pag. 1. read <hi>editas.</hi> p. 17. lege <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 48. r. Monarch. p. 52. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 54. r <hi>De Car.</hi> r. <hi>Cur.</hi> p. 55. for <hi>Pitheus,</hi> r. <hi>Pitſeus.</hi> p. 67. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 68. place <abbr>XXII.</abbr> after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; δ. ibid. f. <hi>r. Cl.</hi> r. <hi>V. Cl.</hi> p. 69. r. <hi>Gazaei</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 70. r. <hi>Sophene.</hi> p. 86. for, I. r. l. p. 87. for <hi>Petar.</hi> r. <hi>Petav.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
